<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The debate at large, between the House of Lords and House of Commons, at the free conference, held in the Painted Chamber, in the session of the convention, anno 1688 relating to the word, abdicated and the vacancy of the throne in the Common's vote.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Lords.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 157 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 81 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A37313</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D506</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14958</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11846075</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11846075</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49847</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A37313)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49847)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 24:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The debate at large, between the House of Lords and House of Commons, at the free conference, held in the Painted Chamber, in the session of the convention, anno 1688 relating to the word, abdicated and the vacancy of the throne in the Common's vote.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Lords.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Commons.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 19-176 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Wickins, and to be sold by the booksellers of London and Westminster,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  II, --  King of England, 1633-1701.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Kings and rulers --  Succession.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Revolution of 1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49847:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49847:1"/>
            <p>THE DEBATE <hi>At Large,</hi> BETWEEN THE HOUSE of LORDS AND HOUSE of COMMONS, AT THE FREE CONFERENCE, HELD In the <hi>Painted Chamber,</hi> in the <hi>Seſſion</hi> of the <hi>CONVENTION, Anno</hi> 1688.</p>
            <p>Relating to the Word, ABDICATED AND THE <hi>Vacancy of the THRONE,</hi> In the COMMON's Vote.</p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>J. Wickins;</hi> And to be Sold by the Bookſellers of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> 1695.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:49847:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:49847:2"/>
            <head>The Debate at large, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="minutes">
               <head>
                  <hi>Martis die</hi> 22 <hi>Januarij,</hi> 1688.</head>
               <p>IN the Convention met, upon his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Letters, this Day in the Houſe of Commons. A Motion being made that the Houſe would appoint a Day, to take into Conſideration the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and State of the Nation.</p>
               <div type="resolution">
                  <head>Reſolved, Nemine Contradicente,</head>
                  <p>That the Houſe, on <hi>Monday,</hi> next, at Ten of the Clock in the Morning, take into Conſideration the State and Condition of the Nation.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="minutes">
               <head>
                  <hi>Lunae</hi> 28 <hi>die Januarij,</hi> 1688.</head>
               <p>The Houſe then (according to the Order of <hi>Tueſday</hi> laſt) proceeded to take into Conſideration the State and Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Nation.</p>
               <div type="resolution">
                  <head>Reſolved,</head>
                  <p>That the Houſe do now Reſolve it ſelf into a Committee of the whole Houſe, to take into Conſideration the State and Condition of the Nation.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Speaker</hi> left the Chair.</p>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Hamden</hi> took the Chair of the Committee.</p>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:49847:3"/>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Speaker</hi> Reaſſumed the Chair.</p>
                  </stage>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Hamden</hi> Reported from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of the whole Houſe that, having taken into Conſideration the Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and State of the Nation, they had agreed upon a Reſolve; which he Read in his Place, and then delivered the ſame in at the Clark's Table, where the ſame being Read, was as followeth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="resolution">
                  <head>Reſolved,</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That King</hi> James <hi>the Second, having Endeavoured to Subvert the Conſtitution of the Kingdom, by Breaking the Original Contract between King and People; and by the Advice of</hi> Jeſuits, <hi>and other Wicked Perſon's, having violated the Fundamental Laws, and With-drawn himſelf out of the Kingdom, hath Abdicated the Government, and that the Throne is thereby Vacant.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="resolution">
                  <head>Reſolved,</head>
                  <p>That this Houſe do agree with the Committee, <hi>That King</hi> James <hi>the Second, having Endeavoured to Subvert the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Kingdom, by Breaking the Original Contract between King and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and by the Advice of the</hi> Jeſuits,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49847:3"/>
                     <hi>and other wicked Perſons, having Violated the Fundamental Laws, and having With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn himſelf out of the Kingdom, hath Abdicated the Government; and that the Throne is thereby Vacant.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="order">
                  <head>Ordered,</head>
                  <p>That Mr. <hi>Hamden</hi> do carry up the ſaid Reſolution to the Lords for their Concurrence. And it was carryed up to the the Lords, by Mr. <hi>Hamden,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="minutes">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sabbath.</hi> 2 <hi>die Feb,</hi> 1688.</head>
               <p>A Meſſage from the Lords to the Commons, by Sir <hi>Miles Cook</hi> and Mr. <hi>Methwin,</hi> Two Maſters in <hi>Chancery</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending the Houſe of Lords.</p>
               <div type="speech">
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>Mr.</hi> SPEAKER,</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Lords have conſidered of the Vote of this Houſe of the</hi> 28th. <hi>of</hi> January <hi>last, to which they concur with Amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; unto which Amendments they deſire the Concurrence of this Houſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>The Amendments made by the Lords to the Votes ſent up to them from this Houſe, the 28th. of <hi>January,</hi> were Read, and are as followeth,</p>
                  <p>L. 8. Inſtead of the Word <hi>Abdicated</hi> Read <hi>Deſerted.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:49847:4"/>
                  <p>L. 9. Leave out theſe Words, <hi>And that the Throne is thereby Vacant.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="minutes">
               <head>
                  <hi>Lunae</hi> 4 <hi>die Feb.</hi> 1688.</head>
               <p>To the Firſt Amendment, Propoſed by the Lords to be made to the Vote of the Commons of the 28th. of <hi>Janu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary,</hi> inſtead of the Word <hi>Abdicated,</hi> to inſert the Word <hi>Deſerted,</hi> the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons do not agree; becauſe the Word <hi>Deſerted</hi> doth not fully expreſs the Concluſion neceſſarily inferred from the Premiſes, which your Lordſhips have agreed; for your Lordſhips have agreed, <hi>That King</hi> James <hi>the Second hath Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to Subvert the Conſtitutions of the Kingdom, by breaking the Original Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract between King and People, and hath Violated the Fundamental Laws, and With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn himſelf out of the Kingdom.</hi> Now the Word <hi>Deſerted</hi> reſpects only the With-drawing, but the Word <hi>Abdica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> reſpects the whole; for which Purpoſe the Commons made choice of it. The Commons do not agree to the Second Amendment to leave out the Words, <hi>And that the Throne is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Vacant.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:49847:4"/>
               <p n="1">1st. Becauſe they conceive, that, as they may well infer from ſo much of their own Vote as your Lordſhips have agreed unto, <hi>That King James the Second has Abdicated the Government, and that the Throne is thereby Vacant;</hi> ſo that if they ſhould admit your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips Amendment that he hath only <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted the Government;</hi> yet, even thence, it would follow that the <hi>Throne is Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant</hi> as to King <hi>James</hi> the Second, <hi>Deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> the Government, being in true Conſtruction, Deſerting <hi>the Throne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2dly. The Commons conceive they need not prove unto your Lordſhips, That, as to any other Perſon, <hi>the Throne is</hi> alſo <hi>Vacant;</hi> your Lordſhips (as they conceive) having already admitted it, by your Addreſſing to the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> the 25th. of <hi>December</hi> laſt, <hi>To take upon him the Adminiſtration of Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Affairs, both Civil and Military; and to take into his Care the Kingdom of</hi> Ireland, <hi>till the meeting of this Conventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> In purſuance of ſuch Letters, and by your Lordſhips renewing the ſame
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49847:5"/>Addreſs to his Highneſs, (as to Publick Affairs, and the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi>) ſince you met, and by Appointing Days of <hi>Publick Thanksgivings</hi> to be Obſerved throughout the whole Kingdom, all which the Commons conceive to apply that it was your Lordſhips Opinion, <hi>That the Throne was Vacant,</hi> and to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify ſo much to the People of this Kingdom.</p>
               <p n="3">3dly. It is from thoſe who are upon the Throne of <hi>England</hi> (when there are any ſuch) from whom the People of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ought to receive Protection; and to whom, for that cauſe, they owe the Allegiance of Subjects; but there being none now from whom they expect <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal</hi> Prrotection, and to whom, for that cauſe, they owe the Allegiance of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, the Commons conceive, <hi>The Throne is Vacant.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="resolution">
                  <head>Reſolved,</head>
                  <p>That the Earl of <hi>Wiltſhire</hi> do go up to the Lords to deſire a Conference upon the Subject matter of the Amendments.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Earl of</hi> Wiltſhire <hi>Reports,</hi> That, he having attended the Lords to deſire
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49847:5"/>a Conference, they had given Anſwer, <hi>That they did conſent to a Conference im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately in the</hi> Painted Chamber.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="resolution">
                  <head>Reſolved,</head>
                  <p>That the Comittee to whom it was referred to prepare Heads of Reaſons at a Conference with the Lords, be the Managers of the ſaid Conference.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Hamden,</hi> Reports from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee appointed to Manage the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with the Lords, That they had Attended the Lords at the Conference, and Communicated unto their Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips the Reaſons why this Houſe doth not Concur with their Lordſhips in the ſaid Amendments.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="minutes">
               <head>
                  <hi>Martis</hi> 5 <hi>die Feb.</hi> 1688.</head>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Hamden</hi> Reports from the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with the Lords, that the Earl of <hi>Nottingham</hi> ſpoke to this Effect,</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">That the Lords had deſired this Conference with the Commons, that they might be as happily United to the Commons in Opinion, as they are inſeparable in their Intereſt; and that they are, at this time, uneaſy that they cannot Concur with the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49847:6"/>Commons in every thing; becauſe it is of ſo great a Concern to the Nation, and from ſo great and Wiſe a Body.</q> That he then delivered what the Lords had done in Reference to the Subject Matter of the laſt Conference, and ſaid; <q rend="margQuotes"> That the Lords did inſiſt upon the Firſt Amendment of the Vote of the Houſe of Commons of the 25th. of <hi>January</hi> laſt, inſtead of the Word <hi>Abdicated,</hi> to have the Word <hi>Deſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1ſt. <q rend="margQuotes">Becauſe the Lords do not find, that the Word <hi>Abdicated</hi> is a Word known to the Common Law of <hi>England</hi> and the Lords hope the Commons will agree to make uſe of ſuch Words only, whereof the Meaning may be underſtood according to Law, and not of ſuch as will be liable to doubtful Interpretations.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2dly. <q rend="margQuotes"> Becauſe in the moſt common Acceptation of the Civil Law, <hi>Abdica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is a Voluntary Expreſs Act of <hi>Renuntiation,</hi> which is not in this Caſe, and doth not follow from the Premiſes, <hi>That King</hi> James <hi>the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49847:6"/>Second, by having With-drawn himſelf, after having endeavoured to Subvert the Conſtitution of the Government, by Break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Original Contract between King and People, and having Violated the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Laws,</hi> may be more properly ſaid to have <hi>Abdicated,</hi> than <hi>Deſerted.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>He ſaid the Lords did Inſiſt on the Second Amendment, to leave out the Words, <hi>And that the Throne is Vacant,</hi> for this Reaſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">For that although the Lords have agreed, that the King has <hi>Deſerted</hi> the Government, and therefore have made Application to the Prince of <hi>Orange, To take upon him the Adminiſtration of the Government, and thereby to Provide for the Peace and Safety of the Kingdom,</hi> yet there can be no other Inference drawn from thence, but only that the Exerciſe of the Government by King <hi>James</hi> the Second is Ceaſed; ſo as the Lords were, and are willing, to ſecure the Nation againſt the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn of the ſaid King into this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; but not that there was either ſuch an <hi>Abdication</hi> by him, or ſuch a
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49847:7"/>
                     <hi>Vacancy in the Throne,</hi> as that the Crown was thereby become <hi>Elective,</hi> which they cannot agree.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="1">I. <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>Becauſe, by the Conſtitution of the Government, the Monarchy is Heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and not Elective.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>Becauſe no Act of the King alone can Barr, or Deſtroy the Right of his Heirs to the Crown; and therefore in Anſwer to the Third Reaſon alledg'd by the Houſe of Commons, If the Throne be Vacant of King</hi> James <hi>the Second, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance is due to ſuch Perſon as the Right of Succeſſion doth belong to.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The Queſtion being put that this Houſe do agree with the Lords in the ſaid Firſt Amendment.</p>
               <p>It paſſed in the Negative.</p>
               <p>The Queſtion being put that this Houſe do agree with the Lords in the ſaid Second Amendment.</p>
               <p>The Houſe divided.</p>
               <p>The Yea's go forth,</p>
               <p>The Tellers for the Yea's, Sir <hi>Joſeph Tredenham,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Gwyn.</hi> 151.</p>
               <p>The Tellers for the No's, Mr. <hi>Colt,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Herbert.</hi> 282.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:49847:7"/>
               <p>And ſo it was Reſolved in the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative.</p>
               <div type="resolution">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſolved,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That a free Conference be deſired with the Lords upon the Subject Matter of the laſt Conference.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="order">
                  <head>Ordered,</head>
                  <p>That it be Referred unto,
<list>
                        <item>Sr. <hi>Robert Howard.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Mr. <hi>Polexfyn.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Mr. <hi>Paul Foley.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Mr. Serj. <hi>Maynard.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Mr. Serjeant <hi>Holt.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Lord <hi>Faukland.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Sr. <hi>George Treby.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Mr. <hi>Sommers.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Mr. <hi>Garraway.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Mr. <hi>Buſcowen.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Sr. <hi>Tho. Littleton.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Mr. <hi>Palmer.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Mr. <hi>Hamden.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Sr. <hi>Henry Capel.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Sr. <hi>Thomas Lee.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Mr. <hi>Secheveril.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Major <hi>Wildman.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Collonel <hi>Birch.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Mr. <hi>Ayres.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Sr. <hi>Richard Temple.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Sr. <hi>Henry Goodrick.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Mr. <hi>Waller.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Sr. <hi>John Guyes.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>To manage the Conference.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="order">
                  <head>Ordered,</head>
                  <p>That Mr. <hi>Dolbin</hi> do go up to the Lords, and deſire a free Conference with the Lords upon the Subject Matter of the laſt Conference.</p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:49847:8"/>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Dolben</hi> Reported, That he having (according to the Order of this Houſe) attended the Lords to deſire a Free Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with their Lordſhips, upon the Subject Matter of the laſt Conference, they had agreed to a Free Conference preſently in the <hi>Painted Chamber.</hi> And the Managers went to a Free Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, at the Free Conference in the <hi>Painted Chamber.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> H—den.</speaker>
                  <p>MY Lords, the Commons have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired this Free Conference from your Lordſhips upon the Subject Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the laſt Conference, that they may make appear unto your Lordſhips that it is not without ſuffitient Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that they are Induced to Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their own Vote, to which your Lordſhips have made ſome Amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and that they cannot agree to thoſe Amendments made by your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips for the ſame Reaſons.</p>
                  <p>My Lords, the Commons do very rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily agree with your Lordſhips, That it
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49847:8"/>is a Matter of the greateſt Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Kingdom in general, its future Peace, and happy Government, and the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Intereſt, both at Home and Abroad, that there be a good Iſſue and Determination of the Buſineſs now in Debate between Both Houſes, and a ſpeedy one as can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt with the Doing of it in the beſt manner. This way of Intercourſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Both Houſes by Free Conference, where there is full Liberty of Objecting, Anſwering, and Replying, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons think the beſt Means to attain this End, and to Maintain a good Correſpondence between Both Houſes, which is ſo neceſſary at all Times, but more eſpecially in the preſent Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture; this, my Lords, will bring Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Strength to the Foundation that ſhall be laid after our late Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſions, and diſcourage our Enemies from Attempting to Undermyne it.</p>
                  <p>It is true, my Lords, the preſent Difference between your Lordſhips and the Commons is only about a few Words; but the Commons think their
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49847:9"/>Words ſo Significant to the Purpoſe for which they are uſed, and ſo Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to the Caſe unto which they are applyed, that in ſo Weighty a Matter as that now in Debate, that they are by no means to be parted with:</p>
                  <p>The Word <hi>Abdicated,</hi> the Commons conceive is of larger Signification than the Word your Lordſhips are pleaſed to uſe <hi>Deſert;</hi> but not too large to be applyed to all the Recitals in the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Commons Vote, to which they meant it ſhould be applyed. Nor ought it to be Reſtrained to a Volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Expreſs Reſignation, only in Word or Writing, Overt-Acts there are that will be ſignificant enough to amount to it.</p>
                  <p>My Lords, that the Common Law of <hi>England</hi> is not acquainted with the Word, it is from the Modeſty of our Law, that it is not willing to ſuppoſe there ſhould be any Unfortunate Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of making uſe of it: And we would have been willing that we ſhould never have had ſuch an Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion as we have to have Recourſe to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49847:9"/>it. Your Lordſhips next Amendment is, that your Lordſhips have left out the laſt Words in the Commons Vote, <hi>And that the Throne is thereby Vacant.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>My Lords, the Commons conceive it is a true Propoſition, and <hi>That the Throne is Vacant;</hi> and, they think, they make it appear, that that is no new Phraſe; neither is it a Phraſe that perhaps ſome of the old Records may be Strangers to; or not well acquainted with: But they think it not chargeable with the Conſequences that your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips have been pleaſed to draw from it, <hi>That it will make the Crown of</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland <hi>become Elective.</hi> If the Throne had been full, we know your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Ships would have aſſigned that, as a Reaſon of your Diſagreement, by tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling us who filled it; and it would be known by ſome Publick Royal Act, which might notify to the People in whom the Kingly Government reſided; neither of which has been done; and yet your Londſhips will not allow the <hi>Throne to be Vacant.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:49847:10"/>
                  <p>My Lords, I am unwilling to detain your Lordſhips longer, from what may be better ſaid for your Lordſhips Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in theſe Matters, by thoſe whoſe Province it is: I am to acquaint your Lordſhips, that the Commons do agree, it is an Affair of very great Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance. Here are other Gentlemen that are appointed to manage this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, and will give their Aſſiſtance to bring it, we hope, to a happy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, in the Agreement of Both Houſes, in this ſo very a Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Point.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> S—rs.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lords, what is appointed me to Speak to, is your Lordſhips Firſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment, by which the Word <hi>Abdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated,</hi> in the Commons Vote, is chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into the Word <hi>Deſerted;</hi> and I am to acquaint your Lordſhips what ſome of the Grounds are, that induced the Commons to inſiſt upon the Word <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated,</hi> and not to agree to your Lordſhips Amendment.</p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:49847:10"/>
                  <p>1st. The Firſt Reaſon your Lordſhips are pleaſed to deliver, as for your Changing the Word is, <hi>That the Word</hi> Abdicated <hi>your Lordſhips do not find, is a Word known to the Common Law of</hi> England; <hi>and therefore ought not to be Uſed:</hi> And the next is, <hi>That the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Acceptation of the Word amounts to a Voluntary expreſs Act of Renuntiation which</hi> (your Lordſhips ſay) <hi>is not, in this Caſe, nor will follow from the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>My Lords, as to the Firſt of theſe Reaſons, if it be an Objection, that the Word <hi>Abdicated</hi> hath not a known Sence in the Common Law of <hi>England,</hi> there is the ſame Objection againſt the Word <hi>Deſerted;</hi> for there can be no Authority, or Book of Law produced, wherein any determined Sence is given to the Word <hi>Deſerted:</hi> So that your Lordſhips firſt Reaſon hath the ſame Force againſt your own Amendment, as it hath againſt the Term uſed by the Commons.</p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:49847:11"/>
                  <p>The Words are both <hi>Latin</hi> Words, and uſed in the beſt Authors, and both of a known Signification; their Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is very well underſtood; though it be true, their Meaning be not the ſame: The Word <hi>Abdicate</hi> doth natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally and properly ſignify <hi>Entirely to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce, Throw off, Diſown, Relinquiſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing or Perſon, ſo as to have no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to do with it;</hi> and <hi>that whether it be done by Expreſs Words, or in Writing,</hi> (which is the Sence your Lordſhips put upon it, and which is properly called <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation or Ceaſion</hi>) or, <hi>by Doing ſuch Acts as are Inconſiſtent with the Holding, or Retaining of the Thing;</hi> which the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons take to be the preſent Caſe, and therefore made Choice of the Word <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate,</hi> as that which they thought did, above all others, moſt properly expreſs that meaning: And in this latter Sence it is taken by Others, and that it is the true Signification of the Word, I ſhall ſhew your Lordſhips out of the beſt Authors:</p>
                  <p>The Firſt I ſhall mention is <hi>Grotius</hi> de Jure Belli &amp; Pacis, L. 2. C. 4. S. 4.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49847:11"/>
                     <hi>Venit enim hoc non ex jure civili, ex jure naturali, quo quiſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſuum poteſt</hi> abdicare, <hi>&amp; ex naturali Praeſumptione qua voluiſſe, quis creditur, quod ſufficienter ſignificavit.</hi> And then he goes on, <hi>Recuſari Haeredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas non tantum verbis, ſed etiam re poteſt, &amp; quovis indicio voluntatis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Another Inſtance, which I ſhall men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to ſhew that for the <hi>Abdicate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> a thing, it is ſuffitient to do an Act which is inconſiſtent with the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining it, though there be nothing of an <hi>Expreſs Renuntiation,</hi> is out of <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi>'s <hi>Lexicon Juridicum,</hi> where he ſays, (<hi>Generum</hi> abdicat, <hi>qui ſponſam repudiat:</hi>) <hi>He that Divorceth his Wife,</hi> Abdicates <hi>his Son in Law.</hi> Here is an <hi>Abdication</hi> without <hi>Expreſs Words;</hi> but is by doing ſuch an Act as doth ſuffitiently ſignify his Purpoſe.</p>
                  <p>The next Author, that I ſhall Quote, is <hi>Briſonius, de Verborum ſignificatione</hi> who hath this Paſſage, <hi>Homo liber qui ſeipſum vendit,</hi> abdicat <hi>ſe ſtatu ſuo:</hi> that is, <hi>He who ſells himſelf, hath thereby done ſuch
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49847:12"/>an Act as cannot conſiſt with his former Eſtate of Freedom;</hi> and is therefore pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſaid, <hi>ſe</hi> abdicaſſe <hi>ſtatu ſuo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Budaeus,</hi> in his Commentaries <hi>ad Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem ſecundam, de Origine Juris,</hi> Expounds the Words in the ſame Sence, Abdicare <hi>ſe Magiſtratu est idem quod abire poenitus Magiſtratu:) He that goes out of his Office of Magiſtracy, let it be in what manner he will, has</hi> Abdicated <hi>the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And <hi>Grotius,</hi> in his Book <hi>de Jure Belli &amp; Pacis,</hi> L. 1. C. 4. S. 9. ſeems to expound the Word <hi>Abdicare,</hi> by <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſte habere pro derelicto:</hi> That is, <hi>That he who hath</hi> Abdicated <hi>any thing, hath ſo far Relinquiſhed it, that he hath no Right of Return to it.</hi> And that is the Sence the Commons put upon the Word: It is an <hi>Entire Alienation of the Thing;</hi> and ſo ſtands in Oppoſition to <hi>Dicate: Di cat qui proprium aliquod facit;</hi> abdicat <hi>qui alienat,</hi> ſo ſays <hi>Pralejus</hi> in his <hi>Lexicon Juris.</hi> It is therefore inſiſted upon as the Proper Word by the Commons.</p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:49847:12"/>
                  <p>But the Word <hi>Deſerted</hi> (which is the Word uſed in the Amendment made by your Lordſhips) hath not only a very doubtful Signification; but in the common Acceptance both of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and Cannon Law, doth ſignify on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a <hi>Bare With-drawing,</hi> a <hi>Temporary Quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of a Thing,</hi>and <hi>Neglect only, which leaveth the Party at Liberty of Returning to it again. Deſertum pro Neglecto,</hi> ſays <hi>Spigelius</hi> in his <hi>Lexicon:</hi> But the Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between <hi>Diſſerere</hi> and <hi>Derelinqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> is expreſly layd down by <hi>Bartolus,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the 8th. Law of 58th. Title of the 11th. Book of the <hi>Code,</hi> and his Words are theſe, <hi>Nota diligenter ex hac Lege, quod aliud est Agrum</hi> diſſerere, <hi>aliud</hi> dere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquire; <hi>qui enim</hi> derelinquit, <hi>ipſum ex poenitentia non revocat: ſed qui</hi> deſeret, <hi>intra biennium poteſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Whereby it appears, my Lords, that, that is called <hi>Deſertion,</hi> which is <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary</hi> and <hi>Relieveable:</hi> That is called <hi>Dereliction,</hi> where there is <hi>no Power of Right to Return.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:49847:13"/>
                  <p>So in the beſt <hi>Latin</hi> Authors, and in the <hi>Civil Law, Deſerere Exercitum</hi> is uſed to ſignify, <hi>Soldiers leaveing their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours,</hi> Cod. Lib. 12. S. 1.</p>
                  <p>And in the <hi>Cannon Law,</hi> to <hi>Deſert a Benefice,</hi> ſignifies no more than to be <hi>Non-Reſident;</hi> ſo is <hi>Calvin</hi>'s <hi>Lexicon, Verb.</hi> Deſert. <hi>ſecund. Canones.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In both Caſes, the Party hath not only a <hi>Right of Returning;</hi> but is <hi>Bound to Return again:</hi> Which, my Lords, as the Commons do not take to be the preſent Caſe; ſo they cannot think that your Lordſhips do; becauſe it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſaid, in One of your Reaſons gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in Defence of the laſt Amendment, <hi>That your Lordſhips have been, and are willing, to ſecure the Nation againſt the Return of King</hi> James; which your Lordſhips would not, in Juſtice, do, if you did look upon it no more than a <hi>Negligent With-drawing,</hi> which leaveth <hi>a Liberty to the Party to Return.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For which Reaſons, my Lords the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49847:13"/>Commons cannot agree to the Firſt Amendment, to inſert the word <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted</hi> inſtead of <hi>Abdicated;</hi> becauſe it doth not, in any ſort, come up to their Sence of the thing: So, they do apprehend, it doth not reach your Lordſhips meaning, as it is expreſſed in your Reaſons; whereas they look upon the Word <hi>Abdicated</hi> to expreſs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly what is to be inferred from that Part of the Vote to which your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips have agreed, <hi>That King</hi> James <hi>the Second, by going about to Subvert the Conſtitution, and by Breaking the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Contract between King and People and by Violating the Fundamental Laws, and With-drawing himſelf out of the Kingdom,</hi> hath thereby Renounced to be a King according to the Conſtitution, by avowing to Govern by a Deſpotick Power, unknown to the Conſtitution, and Inconſiſtent with it; he hath Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced to be a King according to the Law, ſuch a King as he Swore to be at the Coronation, ſuch a King to whom the Allegiance of an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Subject is due; and hath ſet up ano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49847:14"/>kind of Dominion, which is to all Intents an <hi>Abdication</hi> or <hi>Abandoning of his Legal Title,</hi> as fully as if it had been done by expreſs Words,</p>
                  <p>And, my Lords, for theſe Reaſons the Commons do inſiſt upon the Word <hi>Abdicated,</hi> and cannot agree to the Word <hi>Deſerted.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Mr. Serjeant</hi> H—lt.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lords, I am commanded, by the Commons, to aſſiſt in the Management of this Conference, and am to ſpeak to the ſame Point that the Gentleman did, who ſpoke laſt to your Lordſhips Firſt Amendment.</p>
                  <p>As to the Firſt of your Lordſhips Reaſons, for that Amendment, (with Submiſſion to your Lordſhips) I do conceive it not Suffitient to alter the Minds of the Commons; or to induce them to change the Word <hi>Abdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated</hi> for your Lordſhips Word <hi>Deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:49847:14"/>
                  <p>Your Lordſhips Reaſon is, <hi>That it is not a Word that is known to the Common Law of</hi> England. But, my Lords, the Queſtion is not ſo much, Whether it be a Word as Antient as the <hi>Common Law,</hi> (though it may be too) for that will be no Objection againſt the Uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, if it be a Word of a known and certain Signification; becauſe that we think, will Juſtify the Commons making uſe of it, according to your Lordſhips own Expreſſion.</p>
                  <p>That it is an Antient Word, appears by the Authors that have been Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and its frequently met with in the beſt of <hi>Roman</hi> Writers, as <hi>Cicero,</hi> &amp;c. And by the Derivation from <hi>Dico,</hi> an Antient <hi>Latin</hi> Word.</p>
                  <p>That now it is a known <hi>Engliſh</hi> Word, and of a known and certain Significa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with us, I will Quote to your Lordſhips an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Authority, and that is the Dictionary ſet forth by our
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49847:15"/>Countryman <hi>Minſhaw,</hi> who hath the Word <hi>Abdicate</hi> as an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Word, and ſays that it ſignifies to <hi>Renounce,</hi> which is the Signification the Commons would have of it: So that I hope your Lordſhips will not find Fault with their uſeing a Word that is ſo Antient in it ſelf, and that hath ſuch certain Signification in our own Language.</p>
                  <p>Then, my Lords, for that Part of your Lordſhips Objection, <hi>That it is not a Word known to the Common Law of</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, that cannot prevail; for, your Lordſhips very well know, we have ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry few Words in our <hi>Tongue</hi> that are of equal Antiquity with the common Law; your Lordſhips know the Language of <hi>England</hi> is altered greatly in the ſeveral Succeſſions of Time, and the Intermix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of other Nations; and if we ſhould be Obliged to make uſe only of Words then known and in uſe, what we ſhould deliver in ſuch a Dialect would be very Difficult to be Underſtood.</p>
                  <p>Your Lordſhips Second Reaſon, for
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49847:15"/>your Firſt Amendment in changing the Word <hi>Abdicated</hi> for the Word <hi>Deſerted</hi> is, <hi>Becauſe in the moſt common Acceptation of the Civil Law</hi> Abdication <hi>is a Voluntary Expreſs Act of</hi> Renuntiation. That is the general Acceptation of the Word, and, I think, the Commons do ſo uſe the Word in this Caſe, becauſe it hath that Signification: But I do not know, whether your Lordſhips mean a Volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary expreſs Act or formal Deed of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuntiation:</hi> If you do ſo, I confeſs I know of none in this Caſe: But, my Lords, both in the <hi>Common Law</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and the <hi>Civil Law,</hi> and in common Underſtanding, there are Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Acts of <hi>Renuntiation</hi> that are not by Deed; for if your Lordſhips pleaſe to obſerve, the Government and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy is under a Truſt, and any Act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contrary to that Truſt is a <hi>Renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing</hi> of the Truſt, though it be not a <hi>Renouncing</hi> by formal Deed; For it is a plain Declaration, by Act and Deed, though not in Writing, that he, who hath the Truſt, Acting contrary, is a Diſclaimer of the Truſt; eſpecially
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49847:16"/>my Lords, if the Actings be ſuch as are Inconſiſtent with, and Subverſive of this Truſt: For, how can a Man in Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or Senſe, expreſs a greater <hi>Renun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation</hi> of a Truſt, than by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Declarations of his Actions to be quite contrary to that Truſt?</p>
                  <p>This, my Lords, is ſo plain, both in Underſtanding and Practice, that I need do no more but Repeat it again, and leave it with your Lordſhips, <hi>That the doing an Act inconſiſtent with the Being and End of a Thing, or that ſhall not Anſwer the End of that Thing, but quite the contrary, that ſhall be Conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an</hi> Abbication <hi>and Formal</hi> Renunti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation <hi>of that Thing.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Earl of</hi> N—m.</speaker>
                  <p>Gentlemen, you of the Committee of the Commons, we differ from you indeed about the Words <hi>Abdicated</hi> and <hi>Deſerted;</hi> but the main Reaſon of the Change of the Word and Difference, is upon the Account of the Conſequence
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:49847:16"/>drawn in the Concluſion of your Vote, <hi>That the Throne is thereby Vacant:</hi> that is, What the Commons mean by that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, whether you mean it is ſo Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant as to null the Succeſſion in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditary <hi>Line,</hi> &amp; ſo all the <hi>Heirs</hi> to be cut off, which we ſay will make the Crown <hi>Elective?</hi> And it may be fit for us to ſettle that matter firſt, and when we know what the Conſequence of <hi>The Throne being Vacant</hi> means in the Vote as you underſtand it, I believe we ſhall be much better able to ſettle the Difference about the Two Words.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Mr. Serjeant</hi> M—d.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lords, when there is a preſent Defect of One to exerciſe the Admi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſtration of the Government, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, the Declaring a Vacancy, and Proviſion of a Supply for it, can never make the Crown <hi>Elective.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Commons apprehend there is ſuch a Defect now; and, by conſequence a preſent Neceſſity for the Supply of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:49847:17"/>the Government, and that will be next for your Lordſhips Conſideration, and theirs afterwards.</p>
                  <p>If the attempting the utter Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Subject, and Subvertion of the Conſtitution, be not as much an <hi>Abdication</hi> as the attempting of a Father to Cut his Son's Throat, I know not what is.</p>
                  <p>My Lords, the Conſtitution, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Vacancy, is the ſame; the Laws that are the Foundations and Rules of that Conſtitution are the ſame: But if there be in any particular In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, a Breach of that Conſtitution, that will be an <hi>Abdication;</hi> and that <hi>Abdication</hi> will infer a <hi>Vacancy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is not that, the Commons do ſay, <hi>the Crown of</hi> England <hi>is alway and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually Elective;</hi> but it is more neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary that there be a Supply when there is a Defect, and the Doing of that will be no Alteration of the <hi>Monarchy</hi> from a <hi>Succeſſive One</hi> to an <hi>Elective.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:49847:17"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Lord Biſhop of</hi> E—ly.</speaker>
                  <p>Gentlemen, the Two Amendments made by the Lords, to the Vote of the Commons, are as to the Word <hi>Abdica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> and as to the <hi>Vacancy of the Throne:</hi> That <hi>Abdicated</hi> may be Tacitely by ſome <hi>Overt-Acts,</hi> that Gentleman, (I think I may name him without Offence) Mr. <hi>Sommers,</hi> very truly did alledge out of <hi>Grotius:</hi> But, I deſire to know, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Grotius,</hi> that great Author, in Treating on this Subject, doth not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſe this Caution, <hi>If there be a Yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Times: If there be a going away, with a Purpoſe of ſeeking to Recover what is, for the preſent, Left or Forſaken:</hi> In plain <hi>Engliſh, If there were any thing of Force or juſt Fear in the Caſe, that doth void the Notion of</hi> Abdication: I ſpeak not of <hi>Male-Adminiſtration,</hi> now of that hereafter.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Mr. Serjeant</hi> M—rd.</speaker>
                  <p>But, my <hi>Lords,</hi> that is not any Part of the Caſe declared by the Commons
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:49847:18"/>in this Vote, when the whole Kingdom, and the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion, our Laws and Liberties, have been in Danger of being Subverted, an Enquiry muſt be made into the Authors and Inſtruments of this Attempt; and if he, who had the <hi>Adminiſtration</hi> intruſted to him, be found the Author and Actor in it, What can that be, but a <hi>Renuntiation of his Truſt,</hi> and conſequently his Place thereby <hi>Vacant?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>My Lords,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Abdication</hi> (under Favour) is an <hi>Engliſh Word;</hi> and, your Lordſhips have told us, the true Signification of it is a <hi>Renuntiation.</hi> We have indeed, for your Lordſhips Satisfaction, ſhewn its meaning in Foreign Authors; it is more than a <hi>Deſerting</hi> the Government, or <hi>Leaving</hi> it with a Purpoſe of Return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. But we are not, I hope, to go to learn <hi>Engliſh</hi> from Foreign Authors, we can, without their Aid, tell the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our own Tongue.</p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:49847:18"/>
                  <p>If Two of us make a mutual Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to Help and Defend each other from any one that ſhould Aſſault us in a Journey, and that he that is with me turns upon me and breaks my Head, he hath, undoubtedly, <hi>Abdicated</hi> my Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance and Revoked.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Lord Biſhop of</hi> E—ly.</speaker>
                  <p>The Objection of the Lords againſt the Word <hi>Abdicated,</hi> is, <hi>That it is of too large a Signification for the Caſe in Hand.</hi> It ſeems to be acknowledged, that it reacheth a great Way; and therefore the Lords would have a Word made uſe of, which (by the Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of that learned Gentleman) ſignifieth only, <hi>The Ceaſure of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of a Right.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If there be ſuch a Defect as hath been Spoken of, it muſt be Supplyed; there is no Queſtion of that.</p>
                  <p>And I think we have, by another Vote, declared, <hi>That it is Inconſiſtent
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:49847:19"/>with our Laws, Liberties, and Religion, to have a Papiſt to Rule over this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi> Which I take to be only as to the Actual Exerciſe and Adminiſtration of the Government.</p>
                  <p>It is <hi>Grotius</hi> his Diſtinction between a <hi>Right,</hi> and the <hi>Exerciſe of that Right;</hi> and, as there is a Natural Incapacity for the Exerciſe, as Sickneſs, Lunacy, Infancy, Doating Old Age, or an Incurable Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, rendring the Party Unfit for Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Society, as <hi>Leproſie,</hi> or the like; ſo I take it, there is a Moral Incapacity; and, that, I conceive to be a full Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable Perſwaſion in a falſe Religion, contrary to the Doctrine of <hi>Chriſtianity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then there muſt be a Proviſion, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly, made for Supplying this Defect in the Exerciſe, and an Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Government taken care for; becauſe become neceſſary for the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the Government, if he to whom the Right of Succeſſion doth belong makes the Exerciſe of his Government Unpracticable, and our Obedience to
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:49847:19"/>him, Conſiſtently with the Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Religion, Impoſſible; but that, I take it, doth not alter that Right, nor is an <hi>Abdication</hi> of the Right.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Abdication,</hi> no doubt, is by Adapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Word; and well known to <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men converſant in Books: Nor is it Objected, that it is not a Word as Antient, as it may be more Antient than the common Law of <hi>England;</hi> we find it in <hi>Cicero,</hi> and other old <hi>Roman</hi> Writers.</p>
                  <p>But, as to <hi>Cicero,</hi> I would obſerve that there is a double Uſe of the Word; ſometimes it is mentioned with a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and then it ſignifies the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing a Actual Exerciſe of a Right,</hi> as <hi>Abdicare a Triumpho:</hi> And, ſometimes it hath the Accuſative Caſe following it, and then it ſignifies the <hi>Renouncing of the very Right,</hi> as that which was men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, <hi>Abdicare Magiſtratum;</hi> ſo that the Signification (as the Lords in their Reaſon) is doubtful: And ſuch Words,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:49847:20"/>we hope, the <hi>Commons</hi> will not think fit to uſe in a Caſe of this Nature and Conſequence, as ours now in Debate.</p>
                  <p>And beſides, the Lords apprehended that great Inconveniencies will follow upon the Uſe of this Word, if it mean a <hi>Renouncing abſolutely of the Right.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It ſeems the <hi>Commons</hi> do not draw the Word <hi>Abdicated</hi> from His With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing himſelf out of the Kingdom; for then <hi>Deſerted</hi> would (no Doubt) have Anſwered. That <hi>Abdication</hi> is the ſame, whether a Man go out of the Kingdom, or ſtay in it; for it is not to be eſteemed according to the Place, but the Power.</p>
                  <p>If a Man ſtays in the Kingdom, this is <hi>Abdicare,</hi> with a Prepoſition, to <hi>Abdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the Exerciſe of the Government,</hi> but not <hi>the Right of Governing,</hi> according to the Conſtitution; and to ſuch an <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication,</hi> (if it be ſo declared) my Lords, I believe, may ſoon agree.</p>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:49847:20"/>
                  <p>Then, Gentlemen, there is another Diſtinction in thoſe Authors that Writ concerning this Point, which are chiefly the <hi>Civilians;</hi> there may be an <hi>Abdicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> that may <hi>Forfeit the Power of a King only;</hi> and there may be <hi>One,</hi> that may <hi>Forfeit both that and the Crown too.</hi> It is a Diſtinction indeed in other Words, but to the ſame Sence: I will tell you preſently why I uſe it.</p>
                  <p>Thoſe <hi>Abdications</hi> that are of <hi>Power</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, are <hi>Incapacities;</hi> whether thoſe I call Natural and Involuntary, as Defects of Sence, Age, or Body, or the like; or Moral and Voluntary, as Contrariety in Religion; an Inſtance whereof there was lately in <hi>Portugal,</hi> which was a <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture only of the Power,</hi> and not of the <hi>Name</hi> and <hi>Honour of a King;</hi> for though the <hi>Adminiſtration</hi> was put into the youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Brother's Hand, the Pattents, and other Publick Inſtruments ran in the Elder Brothers's Name.</p>
                  <p>This not, without all Doubt, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:49847:21"/>an <hi>Abdication</hi> in the full Extent of the Word; nor do I here (as I ſaid) conſider, whether that the King be gone out of the Kingdom, or ſtay in it; but only, whether he be fit for the <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration,</hi> which muſt be Provided for, be he here, or gone away.</p>
                  <p>But the higheſt Inſtance of an <hi>Abdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> is, when a Prince is not only Unable to execute his Power, but Acts quite contrary to it; which will not be Anſwered by ſo bare a Word as <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I take theſe to be all the Diſtinctions of</hi> Abdications.</p>
                  <p>Now, if this laſt Inſtance of an <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of both Power and Right,</hi> take Place in a <hi>Succeeding Monarchy,</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence will be, <hi>That there is a Forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the whole Right;</hi> and then that <hi>Hereditary Succeſſion</hi> is cut off; which I believe is not intended by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons: There is indeed one Inſtance of the Uſe of ſuch an <hi>Abdication</hi> in
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:49847:21"/>
                     <hi>Monarchy,</hi> and that is, that of <hi>Poland;</hi> and ſuch an <hi>Abdication</hi> there makes the <hi>Throne Vacant;</hi> and thoſe with, and in whom the Power is Inveſted of making Laws, (to wit the Senate) appoint one to Fit it: But that, and whatever other Inſtances of the like kind, theſe may be all of <hi>Elective Kingdoms;</hi> for though ſome of them are, or may be in <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms</hi> now <hi>Hereditary,</hi> yet they were, in thoſe times, <hi>Elective,</hi> and ſince altered into <hi>Hereditary Succeſſions.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But, here is One thing, that is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in this Vote, which I would have well conſidered, for the Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> and that is the <hi>Original Compact:</hi> We muſt think ſure that meant of the <hi>Compact,</hi> that was made at the firſt Time, when the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment was firſt Inſtituted, and the Conditions that each Part of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment ſhould obſerve on their Part, of which this was the moſt Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental, <hi>That King, Lords, and Commons, in Parliament Aſſembled, ſhould have the Power of making New Laws, and altering
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:49847:22"/>of Old Ones:</hi> And that being one Law which ſettles the <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> It is as much Part of the <hi>Original Compact</hi> as any: Then if ſuch a <hi>Caſe</hi> happens, as an <hi>Abdication</hi> in a <hi>Succeſſive Kingdom,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Doubt, the <hi>Compact</hi> being made to the <hi>King,</hi> his <hi>Heirs,</hi> and <hi>Succeſſors,</hi> the <hi>Diſpoſition of the Crown</hi> cannot fall to us till all the <hi>Heirs</hi> do <hi>Abdicate</hi> too. There are indeed many Examples, and too many Interruptions in the <hi>Lineal Succeſſion</hi> of the Crown of <hi>England:</hi> I think, I can inſtance in Seven ſince the Conqueſt, wherein the <hi>Right Heir</hi> hath been put by: But that doth not follow, that every Breach of the Firſt <hi>Original Contract,</hi> gives us Power to <hi>Diſpoſe</hi> of the <hi>Lineal Succeſſion;</hi> eſpecially, I think, ſince the Statutes of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and King <hi>James</hi> the firſt, that have E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed the Oath of <hi>Allegiance</hi> to the <hi>King,</hi> his <hi>Heirs,</hi> and <hi>Succeſſors,</hi> the Law is ſtronger againſt ſuch a <hi>Diſpoſition:</hi> I grant that from King <hi>William</hi> the Firſt, to King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, there has been Seaven Interruptions of the <hi>Legal Line of Hereditary Succeſſion;</hi> but, I ſay, thoſe
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:49847:22"/>Statutes are made ſince that time, and the making of New Laws being as much a Part of the <hi>Original Compact,</hi> as the Obſerving Old Ones, or any thing elſe, we are Obliged to purſue thoſe Laws, till altered by the <hi>Legiſlative Power,</hi> which ſingly, or joyntly, without the Royal Aſſent, I ſuppoſe, we do not pretend to; and theſe <hi>Laws</hi> being made ſince the laſt Interruption, we are not to go by any Preſident that was made before the making thoſe <hi>Laws.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So that, all that I conceive, ought to be meant by our Vote is, <hi>But a Setting aſide the Perſon that Broke the Contract: And, in a Succeſſive Kingdom, an</hi> Abdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation <hi>can only be a Forfeiture, as to the Perſon himſelf.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I hope, and am perſwaded, that both <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> do agree in this, <hi>Not to break the Line of Succeſſion, ſo as to make the Crown Elective:</hi> And, if that be declared, that this <hi>Abdication</hi> of King <hi>James</hi> the Second reacheth no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than himſelf; and that it is to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:49847:23"/>in the <hi>Right Line of Succeſſion,</hi> that I hope, will make all of One Mind, in this important Affair.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Earl of</hi> C—n.</speaker>
                  <p>As I remember, Mr. <hi>Sommers,</hi> who ſpoke to the ſignification of the Word <hi>Abdicated,</hi> did Quote <hi>Grotius, Galvin</hi>'s <hi>Lexicon,</hi> and other Civil Lawyers, where the Expreſs Words make it to be a <hi>Voluntary Act;</hi> and ſo are all the Inſtances that ever I Read or Heard of; that is, there either was ſome <hi>Formal Deed of Renuntiation,</hi> or <hi>Reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation;</hi> or ſome <hi>Voluntary Act done of the Party's own;</hi> and ſuch whereby they have ſhewn they did Deveſt themſelves of the Royalties.</p>
                  <p>I think truly, Gentlemen, it is very apparent that the King, in this Caſe, hath done nothing of this Nature: It is indeed ſaid, by that learn'd and inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Gentleman, Mr. <hi>Sommers,</hi> That it may ariſe from the Facts, that in the Vote it has been declar'd he hath done, <hi>breaking
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:49847:23"/>the Fundamental Laws, and the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Contract: and endeavouring to Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the Conſtitution of the Kingdom.</hi> I will not diſcourſe the Particulars that have been alledged, to make out this Charge; But I may ſay this much in General, That this <hi>Breaking the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Contract,</hi> is a Language that hath not been long uſed in this Place; nor known in any of our <hi>Law-Books,</hi> or Publick Records: It is ſprung up, but as taken from ſome late Authors, and thoſe none of the beſt received; and the very Phraſe might bear a great Debate, if that were now to be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to. Mr. <hi>Sommers</hi> did likewiſe ſpeak ſomething to the particular Caſe, and the Grounds of the Vote; he ſaid, <hi>The King is Bounded by Law, and bound to perform the Laws made, and to be made.</hi> That is not denyed; I would take Notice, that his Obligation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto doth not proceed from his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation Oath; for our Law ſaith, <hi>He is as much King before he is Crowned, as he is afterwards; And there is a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Allegiance due to him from the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:49847:24"/>immediately upon the Deſcent of the Crown upon him.</hi> And though it is a very requiſite Ceremony, to put him under a farther Obligation by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of his Oath; yet I think it will not, nor can be denyed but that, as King, he was bound to Obſerve the <hi>Laws</hi> before; and no Body will make that Oath to be the <hi>Original Contract,</hi> as I ſuppoſe.</p>
                  <p>But, my Lords and Gentlemen, if you do admit that it was never intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by the Houſe of <hi>Commons,</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late any further than to this King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, I believe my own Opinion would concur to ſecure us againſt his Return to Govern us: But then, Why is there ſuch a Contention about a Word? Doth all this imply more than <hi>Deſertion?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But it is ſaid, that <hi>Abdication</hi> doth imply a <hi>perfect Renuntiation,</hi> which I cannot ſee how it is in this Caſe, <hi>ſo as to leave us at Liberty to ſupply as we pleaſe, and break the Line of Succeſſion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:49847:24"/>
                  <p>Mr. Serjeant <hi>Maynard</hi> ſays, <hi>That it is not indeed to make the Government per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually Elective.</hi> I would know, what he means by <hi>Perpetually:</hi> Our Breaking through the Line now, by a Choice out of the Lineal Courſe, is an Alteration and a Preſident: And why may not others take the ſame Liberty we doe? And, Will not that make it <hi>Perpetually Elective?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But truly, I think, no Act of ours can alter the <hi>Lineal Succeſſion;</hi> for, by all the Laws we have now in Being, our Government appears to be <hi>Heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> in a Right Line of <hi>Deſcent:</hi> And up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any Deſcent, when any one ceaſeth to be <hi>King, Allegiance</hi> is by Law due to his <hi>Legal Heirs,</hi> as <hi>Succeſſor,</hi> before Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation, as after,</p>
                  <p>I was in great Hopes that you would have offer'd ſomething in Anſwer to One of my Lord's Reaſons againſt that part of the Vote, which declares, <hi>The Throne to be Vacant.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:49847:25"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That no Act of the King's alone can Bar or Deſtroy the Right of his Heir to the Crown, which is Hereditary, and not Elective.</hi> And then, if this matter goes no farther than King <hi>James</hi> the Second, in his own Perſon, How comes the <hi>Vacancy</hi> and the <hi>Supply</hi> to be Devolved upon the People? For if he only be ſet Aſide, then it is apparent, whether the Crown is to go, to the Perſon that hath the next <hi>Right of Succeſſion;</hi> and conſequently there is no <hi>Vacancy.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Earl of</hi> N—m.</speaker>
                  <p>Gentlemen, I would not Protract Time, which is now ſo neceſſary to be Husbanded; nor perplex Debates a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout any Affair like that which lies now before us, It is not a Queſtion barely about Words, but Things, which we are now Diſputing.</p>
                  <p>The Word <hi>Abdicated,</hi> it is agreed by Mr. <hi>Sommers,</hi> is a Word of Art; and he hath told us what its Significa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is, from thoſe that are Skilled
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:49847:25"/>in the Art to which it belongs: He doth acknowledge that it is no Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>word among <hi>Engliſh</hi> Lawyers; nor known to the Common Law: But then he ſaith, neither is the Word, uſed by the Lords, <hi>Deſerted.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I agree to him, that neither the One, or the Other are Words uſed in our Law; but the Inference I would draw thence is this, That we have no words applicable to this Caſe; becauſe we never before had ſuch a Caſe; and we muſt not draw Inferences of Law in ſuch a Caſe, that are not deducible from Rules well known in our Laws.</p>
                  <p>I will not Diſpute what the Sence of the word <hi>Abdication</hi> is in the <hi>Civil Law;</hi> but that it is a <hi>Civil Law</hi> Word, is agreed to by me; and if it be, for that Reaſon, I am againſt uſing of it; becauſe I am ſo much in Love with our own Laws, that I would uſe no VVords in a Caſe that ſo much concerns our <hi>Legal Conſtitution,</hi> but what are fetched from thence.</p>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:49847:26"/>
                  <p>I hope I ſhall never ſee our old Laws altered; or if they be, <hi>God</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid, we ſhould be the Voluntary A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents in ſuch an Alteration.</p>
                  <p>But, then we are told the Word <hi>Deſerted</hi> doth not reach our Caſe; becauſe the Signification of the Word is but a <hi>Temporary Leaveing,</hi> or <hi>Forſaking of his Power, which he may Reaſſume;</hi> nay, <hi>which in ſome Caſes there is a Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty upon him to Return unto.</hi> If that were all, Mr. <hi>Sommers</hi> hath given him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf an Anſwer to that Objection, out of what he alledges of the Lords Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who have declared that they are willing, <hi>To ſecure the Nation againſt the Return of King</hi> James <hi>into this Kingdom; and will therefore concur with the Commons in any Act that ſhall be thought neceſſary to prevent ſuch his Return:</hi> ſo that it ſhould ſeem we were agreed in that Matter; and if that were the Point we ſhould find Words proper, ſoon enough, to expreſs our meaning by.</p>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:49847:26"/>
                  <p>But, I find neither of theſe Words will, on the One Side or on the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, be allowed to ſignify this Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; therefore we ſhould (as I take it) come preſently to think of ſome other that would. But, the Reaſons why my Lords did chiefly inſiſt upon the Alteration of the Word <hi>Abdicated</hi> was, <hi>Becauſe they did apprehend, that it being a Word not known to our Laws, there might be other Inferences drawn from it than they do apprehend our Laws will War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, from the Caſe, as it is ſtated in the Fact of this Vote; and, as they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, is done in the concluding of the Throne's being Vacant.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Therefore, I think it would ſhorten the preſent Debate, if we did ſettle that Point firſt; and, as we frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Parliamentary Proceedings, Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pone this, and that Paragraph in a Bill, till ſome others that may be thought fit to be Determined firſt, be agreed to, ſo we ſhould Poſtpone the Debate about the word <hi>Abdicate,</hi> till the <hi>Vacancy of the Throne</hi> be Settled; for
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:49847:27"/>if we were ſure that the Throne were, or were not Vacant, we ſhould eaſily light upon what Word were Proper to be uſed in this Caſe.</p>
                  <p>I ſhould therefore Propoſe, that we might Debate that firſt, becauſe if there be an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Word of known Signification in our Law, which ſhould ſignify no more than <hi>Renouncing for a Man's ſelf;</hi> and which would not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to ſo much as <hi>Setting aſide the Right of Others,</hi> that Word may be uſed; and, if no other, the Word <hi>Renouncing</hi> it ſelf may be taken, which would be beſt agreed to.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Acting againſt a Man's Trust</hi> (ſays Mr. Serjeant <hi>Holt) Is a Renuntiation of that Truſt.</hi> I agree it is a <hi>Violation of his Truſt to Act contrary to it;</hi> and he is accountable, for that <hi>Violation,</hi> to Anſwer what the Truſt ſuffers out of his own Eſtate: But I deny it to be preſently a <hi>Renuntiation</hi> of the Truſt, and that ſuch a one is no longer a Truſtee.</p>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:49847:27"/>
                  <p>I beg his Pardon, if I differ from him in Opinion, whom I acknowledge to have much more Learning in his Profeſſion than I can pretend unto; But if the Law be, as he ſays, in a <hi>private Caſe;</hi> then I muſt beg leave to forbear giving my Opinion in a Caſe of this <hi>publick Nature</hi> that is now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us, till I know what ſuch a <hi>Truſt</hi> is, and what the Law ſays in ſuch a Caſe.</p>
                  <p>If indeed, you do pretend <hi>That the Throne is Vacant,</hi> and Both Houſes agree to that Concluſion; I think it will be no matter what VVord is uſed about it: But, if we do not agree unto that Concluſion; I think it will be afterwards eaſy to ſhew which is the fitteſt Word to be ſtood upon; or to agree on ſome other.</p>
                  <p>I Pray therefore (to ſhorten the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate) that you Gentlemen would ſpeak to this Point firſt; and when that is Reſolved, I hope we ſhall eaſily come to an Agreement about the Other.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:49847:28"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Sir</hi> George T—by.</speaker>
                  <p>I think, my Lords, that we may not conſent to begin at the End, and firſt to enquire of the Concluſion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Premiſes are ſettled: For the <hi>Vacancy of the Throne</hi> follows, as an Inference drawn from the Acts of the King's, which are expreſſed moſt ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the Word <hi>Abdication;</hi> and to enquire what the Conſequence is, when the Fact is doubtful, from which the Conſequence is to enſue, is begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the wrong End; till we ſtate the Fact, we can aſſign no Conſequence at all to it: Therefore, my Lords, I think the preſent Debate is to begin, where the Difference between the Two Houſes doth begin, and that is at the Word <hi>Abdicated;</hi> and, when that is over, we ſhall regularly come to the other Point in Difference.</p>
                  <p>We are gone back too far, when we offer to enquire into the <hi>Original Contract,</hi> Whether any ſuch thing is known or underſtood in our Law or
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:49847:28"/>Conſtitution? or, Whether it be new Language among us? And I offer this to your Lordſhips Conſideration for Two Reaſons,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>First,</hi> It is a Phraſe and Thing uſed by the Learned Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> in his Book of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Polity,</hi> whom I mention as a valuable Authority, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one of the beſt Men, the beſt Church Man, and the moſt Learned of our Nation in his time, and his Works are very worthily Recommended by the Teſtimony of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt; He alloweth, <hi>That Government did Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally begin by Compact and Agreement.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But I have yet a greater Authority than this, to influence this Matter, and that is your Lordſhips own, who have agreed to all the Vote, but this Word <hi>Abdicated,</hi> and <hi>The Vacancy of the Throne:</hi> And therefore ſo much enough to be ſaid to that; and go back to Debate what is not in Difference, is to confound our ſelves, inſtead of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to compoſe Differences.</p>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:49847:29"/>
                  <p>And truly, my Lords, by what is now Propoſed, I think, we are deſired to go as much too far fowards, when the <hi>Vacancy of the Throne</hi> is propoſed to be the Queſtion to be firſt Diſputed before the <hi>Abdication,</hi> from which it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>rred.</p>
                  <p>But ſure I am, it is very much beyond what the Vote before us doth lead us unto, <hi>To talk of the Right of thoſe in the Succeſſion:</hi> For that goes farther <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>han the very laſt Part of the Vote; and it is ſtill to lead us yet far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to ſay any thing about make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Crown Elective:</hi> For, I hope, when we come to anſwer your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips Reaſons, we ſhall eaſily make it out, that it is not in this Caſe; neither was there any Occaſion given by this Vote to infer any ſuch thing: VVe ſhall therefore, keep the Points as they are both in Order of Place, in the Vote, and of Reaſon in the thing; and, as we have done hither, to ſpeak
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:49847:29"/>to the words <hi>Abdicated</hi> and <hi>Deſerted,</hi> the words to be Diſputed about in the Firſt Place. Another Lord did give One Reaſon againſt the uſeing the VVord <hi>Abdicated, Becauſe it is a Word belongs to the</hi> Civil Law, and ſaid, <hi>He would by no means exchange our own</hi> Engliſh <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law for that.</hi> I intirely concur with that Noble Lord in that Point; but he did agree to us alſo, <hi>That there is no ſuch Word in our Common Law as</hi> Deſerted; that is, <hi>which ſhould ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, by the Stamp the Law puts upon it, any Sence applicable to the Matter in Hand.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then, if we muſt not uſe our VVord, becauſe unknown to our Common Law; neither muſt we uſe your Lordſhips for the ſame Reaſon, and ſo ſhall be at an entire loſs what VVord to uſe; and ſo, indeed, they may well come to conſider the Concluſion firſt, who leave us at Uncertainties on what Terms we are to Diſcourſe; and there cannot be a greater Confuſion in any Debate, than to ſtate a Concluſion without the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes;
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:49847:30"/>which we muſt doe, if we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not agree how to word the Fact we infer from.</p>
                  <p>My Lords, I ſhall not much differ from what, in general, has been ſaid concerning the Sence of the Word <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated;</hi> for it ſeems to be agreed on all Hands that it is a <hi>Renuntiation:</hi> Neither, will I contend for an <hi>Invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary Abdication;</hi> becauſe I think it means a <hi>Voluntary Act:</hi> But truly what your Lordſhips mean, in your Reaſon againſt it, by the Word <hi>Expreſs,</hi> I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſo well underſtand.</p>
                  <p>That a King may <hi>Renounce</hi> his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, I think, may be made out both in Law &amp; Fact, as well as any other <hi>Renun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation;</hi> and that, as far as I can diſcern, by your Lordſhips Reaſons, and this Days Debate hitherto, is not intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be denyed by any: Indeed ſome of my Lords have told us, <hi>That there 'tis meant of the Exerciſe of a Right which may be Renounced, without Renouncing that Right.</hi> Whether that be a true
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:49847:30"/>Diſtinction, or no, is not very Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial: but if it be, that the very Kingſhip it ſelf (as including a Right to Govern) may be <hi>Renounced,</hi> and hath been, it will be no Difficulty to make out, by Inſtances in all Countries, not only where the Crown is, or was <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lective;</hi> but alſo where it was <hi>Heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary</hi> and <hi>Succeſſive.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If a King will <hi>Reſign</hi> or <hi>Renounce,</hi> he may do ſo, as particularly <hi>Char.</hi> 5th.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Earl of</hi> P—k.</speaker>
                  <p>That was an expreſs Solemn <hi>Renun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Sir</hi> George T—by.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lords, the particular manner of Doing it, is (I take it) not matter in Debate juſt now before us, till it be ſettled whether a King can <hi>Abdicate</hi> at all, or <hi>Reſign,</hi> or <hi>Renounce</hi> his <hi>Kingſhip</hi> at all; this then being granted <hi>That a King may Renounce, may Reſign, may
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:49847:31"/>Part with his Office, as well as the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of it;</hi> then the Queſtion indeed is, <hi>Whether this King hath done ſo, or no?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That he may do it, I take it for gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, it being an Act of the VVill: Then let us now inquire into the Facts, as ſet out in the Vote, VVhether this VVill of his be manifeſt? for that you have heard it may be diſcovered ſeveral ways; the Diſcovery may be by VVri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, it may be by VVords, it may be by Facts: <hi>Grotius</hi> himſelf, and all Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, that treat of this Matter and the Nature of it do agree, <hi>That if there be any Word, or Action that doth ſuffiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently manifeſt the Intention of the Mind and Will, to part with his Office; that will amount to an</hi> Abdication, <hi>or</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing.</p>
                  <p>Now, my Lords, I beg leave to put this Caſe, That had King <hi>James</hi> the II. come here into the Aſſembly of Lords and Commons, and expreſſed himſelf in VVriting, or VVords, to this Purpoſe, I was Born an Heir to the Crown of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:49847:31"/>
                     <hi>England,</hi> which is a Government limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Laws, made in full Parliament by King, Nobles, and Commonalty; and, upon the Death of my laſt Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor, I am in Poſſeſſion of the Throne; and, now I find, I cannot make Laws without the Conſent of the Lords and Repreſentatives of the Commons in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; I cannot ſuſpend Laws that have been ſo made, without the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of my People; this indeed is the Title of Kingſhip I hold by <hi>Original Contract,</hi> and the Fundamental Conſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tutions of the Government, and my Succeſſion to, and Poſſeſſion of, the Crown; on theſe Terms is Part of that <hi>Contract;</hi> this Part of the <hi>Contract</hi> I am weary of, I do Renounce it, I will not be obliged to Obſerve it; nay, I am un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der an invincible Obligation not to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with it; I will not Execute the Laws that have been made; nor ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer others to be made, as my People ſhall deſire, for their Security in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, Liberty, and Property, which are the Two main Parts of the Kingly Office in this Nation. I ſay, ſuppoſe
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:49847:32"/>he had ſo expreſt himſelf, doubtleſs this had been a plain <hi>Renouncing</hi> of that <hi>Legal Regular Title</hi> which came to him by Deſcent: If then he, by Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Acts, ſuch as are enumerated in the Vote, has declared as much, or more than theſe Words can amount to, then he hath thereby declared his Will to <hi>Renounce the Government:</hi> He hath, by theſe Acts mentioned, mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly declared that he will not Govern according to the Laws made; Nay, he cannot ſo doe; for he is under a Strict Obligation, (yea the ſtricteſt) and Superior to that of the <hi>Original Compact</hi> between King and People, to Act contrary to the Laws, or to Suſpend them.</p>
                  <p>By the Law, he is to adminiſter Juſtice; aand to Execute his Office ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Tenour of thoſe Laws; and, the Coronation Oath obligeth him likewiſe to conſent to ſuch Laws as the People ſhall chooſe: But on the contrary, by that unfortunate Perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion (in Point of Religion) that he
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:49847:32"/>hath Embraced, he is Obliged to Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend the Laws that defend the Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Religion, and to Treat it, as it has been (as we well know) cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, as the <hi>Northern Hereſy;</hi> and, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Pain of Damnation to Extirpate it: And, in order to it, did ſet aſide and Repeal all the legal Fences of it, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Conſent of Parliament. What the Endeavours and Practices of that kind have been in the laſt Reign, I ſuppoſe, we are not now to be told of, or Inſtructed in; and if (as is very Plain) this doth amount to a mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Declaration of his Will, no longer to Retain the Exerciſe of his Kingly Office, thus Limitted, thus Reſtrained, then in common Sence, as well as le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Acceptation, he has ſuffitiently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared his <hi>Renouncing of the very Office:</hi> As for his Departure out of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, 'tis not material, whether it was Voluntary or Involuntary; but it is ſuffitient that his Actings declare, <hi>quo Animo,</hi> he went away, he no longer would purſue what he deſigned; and was ſo ſtrongly Obliged unto the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:49847:33"/>by the Duty of his Office and Relation, and the Obligation of the <hi>Original Contract;</hi> as likewiſe his own Coronation Oath, and then he deſires no longer to be here.</p>
                  <p>So that, taking both theſe things together, that he will not,; nay he cannot (as thus perſwaded in Point of Religion) Govern according to Law; and thereupon hath withdrawn him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf out of the Kingdom: It is a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt Declaration of his Expreſs <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing</hi> and <hi>Parting with his Kingly Office:</hi> And therefore I cannot depart from inſiſting upon this word <hi>Abdica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> which doth ſo well correſpond to the Fact of the Caſe, and ſo well expreſs the true Meaning of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in their Vote: Nor can we Conſent to the <hi>Poſtponeing</hi> this Point, till the other about <hi>The Vacancy of the Throne,</hi> be determined; for this is the very Foundation upon which we are to to proceed, for Eſtabliſhing the Superſtructure of the other Concluſion.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:49847:33"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Earl of</hi> N—m.</speaker>
                  <p>This Learned Gentleman that ſpoke laſt, ſays, <hi>It is neceſſary to prefer the Premiſes before the Concluſion, as being the Foundation of the Superſtructure.</hi> Truly, I apprehend that this word <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated</hi> was part of the <hi>Concluſion,</hi> and not of the <hi>Premiſes;</hi> The Vote runs thus, <hi>That by Breaking the Original Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, having endeavoured to ſubvert the Conſtitution of the Kingdom, and having withdrawn himſelf out of the Kingdom, he has Abdicated the Government, and the Throne is thereby Vacant.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I take it to be (as I ſay) part of the <hi>Concluſion,</hi> the other part being joyned by a Copulative; therefore that which is but the other part of the <hi>Concluſion,</hi> is not to be inferred from the other part of the <hi>Premiſes.</hi> But take it to be (as you ſay) that <hi>The Vacancy of the Throne is another Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Concluſion from all that preceded, as the</hi> Premiſes, <hi>and therefore it is to be
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:49847:34"/>conſidered laſt;</hi> I would then beg the Favour of You, Gentlemen of the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> to anſwer me one Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on about this Point of <hi>Abdication,</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you mean by <hi>Abdication</hi> a Renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing for Himſelf, or for himſelf and his Heirs.</p>
                  <p>If You mean only <hi>Abdication</hi> for Himſelf, it will have a different Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon the Debate and Reſolution of the Caſe, as to the meaning of that You call the <hi>Concluſion;</hi> for then, <hi>How can the Throne be Vacant?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But if it be meant for himſelf and his Heirs, then I apprehend it is no more than what you ſay at the end, <hi>That the Throne is indeed Vacant;</hi> and then this <hi>Abdication</hi> cannot be Part of the <hi>Premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> but muſt be the ſame Thing with, or Part of, the <hi>Concluſion:</hi> I will not undertake to diſpute, Whether a King of <hi>England</hi> may, or may not, Renounce his Kingdom? For my own Part, I think he can, and I may go ſo far in Agreement with thoſe that have ſpoken
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:49847:34"/>to this Point, <hi>To yield that he may do it by implicit Acts, contrary to the Kingly Office.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For a <hi>King</hi> to ſay, He will not govern according to Law; and for a <hi>King</hi> to act wholly contrary to Law, and do that which would Subvert the Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is (I think) the ſame thing.</p>
                  <p>But then I muſt ſay alſo, That I think there is a Difference between <hi>Saying ſo,</hi> and <hi>Doing ſomething</hi> inconſiſtent with what the Laws require; for every De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viation from the Law is a kind of Breach of the fundamental Laws; for I know no Law, as Laws, but what are Fundamental Conſtitutions; as the Laws are neceſſary, ſo far as to ſupport the Foundation.</p>
                  <p>But if every Tranſgreſſion or Viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Law, by the Prince's Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivance or Command, were ſuch a Breach of the Fundamental Laws, as would infer an <hi>Abdication,</hi> then were it in vain to call any of his <hi>Miniſters</hi>
                     <pb n="84" facs="tcp:49847:35"/>or <hi>Officers</hi> to Account for any ſuch Action.</p>
                  <p>Then the Action is the <hi>King</hi>'s, and not <hi>Theirs;</hi> and then adieu to the Maxim of, <hi>A King's not doing Wrong:</hi> And we may have Recourſe to that other <hi>Reſpondent Superior,</hi> as more effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual Satisfaction.</p>
                  <p>I take this Matter to be ſo plain, as to the Diſtinction that I have men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, that nothing can be more; and it has been thought ſo eſſentially neceſſary to have it clear and manifeſt, That thoſe two great Inſtances of <hi>Edward</hi> the Second, and <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, were expreſs ſolemn Renuncia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and thoſe confirm'd in <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> by the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> by the Act of Depoſing them.</p>
                  <p>Therefore I cannot infer from the Facts enumerated in the Vote, That this ſhould be an <hi>Abdication</hi> for himſelf and his Heirs.</p>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:49847:35"/>
                  <p>But therefore, becauſe in this firſt Point it is diſputable, what is meant by a Word not known of Significati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Law; it might, I think, do well to conſider what is to be inferred from it: And therefore all I have now ſaid, is only to this purpoſe, That either Both make One <hi>Concluſion,</hi> or elſe the Latter cannot be inferred from the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Sir</hi> George T—y.</speaker>
                  <p>I beg Leave to ſay ſomething to what this Noble Lord has laſt ſpoke unto: When I call this Point of the <hi>Vacancy of the Throne</hi> a <hi>Concluſion,</hi> I did not mean altogether to exclude <hi>Abdication</hi> from being a <hi>Concluſion</hi> from the Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars enumerated before; for indeed it is the nature of a double <hi>Concluſion;</hi> One from the particular Facts mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, That thereby King <hi>James</hi> has <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated</hi> the <hi>Government.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:49847:36"/>
                  <p>The Other, from the <hi>Abdication,</hi> That thereby the <hi>Throne is Vacant:</hi> By the inſtanced Acts, he hath <hi>Abdicated</hi> the <hi>Government;</hi> and by his <hi>Abdicating</hi> the <hi>Government,</hi> the <hi>Throne</hi> is vacant. As to the reſt of that which his Lordſhip is pleaſed to ſay, I perceive he does (as he muſt) agree to me, That a <hi>King</hi> may Renounce by Acts as well as Words, or Writings.</p>
                  <p>But then, I would add, and agree with his Lordſhip alſo, That <hi>God forbid every Violation of the Law, or Deviation from it, ſhould be reckon'd an Abdication of the Government.</hi> I deſire to deliver my ſelf from the Imputation of any ſuch abſurd Conceit.</p>
                  <p>When a King breaks the Law in ſome few particular Inſtances, it may be ſufficient to take an Account of it from thoſe evil Miniſters that were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental in it, why ſuch a thing was done, which was againſt Laws? Why
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:49847:36"/>ſuch a Law was not Executed by them, whoſe Duty it was to ſee it put in Execution? You may, in ordinary Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of breaking the Law, have Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in the ordinary Courts and courſe of Juſtice.</p>
                  <p>But ſure! He does not take this to be ſuch a Caſe, or theſe to be ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Violations of the Law; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the extraordinary Caſes, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Remedy's to be recurred unto; for the King having a limited Authority, by which he was obliged to keep the Laws made, as to the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutive part of the Government, and to obſerve the Conſtitution for making ſuch New Laws as the People ſhould find neceſſary, and preſent him for his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; when he doth <hi>Violate,</hi> not a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Law, but all the Fundamentals; nor Injure a particular Perſon in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Liberty, or Property, but falls upon the whole Conſtitution it ſelf, what doth all this ſpeak?</p>
                  <p>He therein ſaith, <hi>I will no more keep
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:49847:37"/>within my limited Authority, nor hold my Kingly Office upon ſuch Terms.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Title I had by the Original Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract between</hi> King <hi>and</hi> People; <hi>I Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce that, and will aſſume another Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to my ſelf; that is, ſuch a Title, as by which I may Act as if there were no ſuch</hi> Law <hi>to Circumſcribe my Authority.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Where ſhall any Man come to have Redreſs in ſuch a Caſe as this, when the Malefactor comes to be Party, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom all Applications for Relief and Redreſs from Injuries ſhould be made, and ſo he himſelf ſhall be a Judge of his own Breaches of Law. This moſt apparently was the Caſe as to the <hi>Quo Warranto's,</hi> which was a plain Deſign to ſubvert the Conſtitution in the very Foundation of the <hi>Legiſlature.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is becauſe the King hath thus vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated the Conſtitution, by which the Law ſtands, as the Rule both of the King's Government, and the Peoples O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, that we ſay, He hath <hi>Abdicated</hi>
                     <pb n="89" facs="tcp:49847:37"/>and Renounced the Government; for all other particular Breaches of the Law, the Subject may have Remedy in the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Courts of Juſtice, or the extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Court of Parliamentary Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: But were ſuch an Attempt as this is, made on the Eſſence of the Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it is not We that have brought our ſelves into this ſtate of Nature, but Thoſe who have reduced our legal well-eſtabliſh'd Frame of Government into ſuch a ſlate of Confuſion, as we are now ſeeking a Redreſs unto.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Earl of</hi> R—er.</speaker>
                  <p>The <hi>Lords</hi> have given their Reaſons why they altered the word <hi>Abdicated;</hi> becauſe it is a word not known to the Common Law, and of doubtful Signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication: Therefore it would be well if the <hi>Commons</hi> would pleaſe to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs their own Meaning by it. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve my Lords would be induced to Agree, that the King hath <hi>Abdicated,</hi> that is, <hi>Renounced the Government,</hi> for himſelf. If you mean no further than
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:49847:38"/>that; and if You do ſo, Why ſhould You not be pleaſed to explain your ſelves, that every one may know how the Matter ſtands, and to preſerve a good Correſpondence between Both Houſes, in ſuch a Juncture and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction as this?</p>
                  <p>But if you do mean any thing more by it, than <hi>Abdication</hi> for Himſelf only, tho' their Lordſhips ſhould agree to the uſing of the word <hi>Abdicated;</hi> yet this would prove a greater Argument againſt their Agreeing in the Other Point, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the <hi>Vacancy of the Throne?</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, we would be glad to have you explain your ſelves, what you mean by it.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Then there was a little Pauſe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </stage>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> H—en.</speaker>
                  <p>If the Lords have nothing further to offer upon this Point, it will be fit for Us to go on to the other Amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, made by the Lords to Our Vote.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:49847:38"/>
               <stage>
                  <p>
                     <hi>No</hi> Lord <hi>offering to ſpeak, the</hi> Commons <hi>proceeded to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Amendment.</hi>
                  </p>
               </stage>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Sach—rel.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lords, Your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> Second Amendment to the <hi>Commons</hi> Vote, (to wit, To leave our the Words, <hi>And that the Throne is thereby Vacant</hi>) the <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> cannot agree with Your Lordſhips to that Amendment; and they do conceive they have many and great Reaſons why they ſhould not do it.</p>
                  <p>But, my Lords, They very much wonder, how it comes here to be laid upon Them (as it ſeems to be, by one of your Lordſhips Reaſons) That they, by uſing thoſe Words of <hi>Abdication</hi> and <hi>Vacancy,</hi> ſignifie an intention of making an Alteration of the Conſtitution of the Government.</p>
                  <p>I would not miſrepreſent Your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:49847:39"/>Words, or miſrepreſent Your Meaning: But you are pleaſed to ſay, <hi>That you cannot agree to ſuch an Abdica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Vacancy, as that the Crown ſhould thereby become Elective:</hi> As if the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> had Thoughts of making the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom Elective, when no ſuch thing was either meant by Them, or can be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted from their Words.</p>
                  <p>But, my Lords, One Reaſon why they differ from You is, They think (up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the nature of your Proceedings) they are in the Right, to inſiſt upon their Vote, as they ſent it up to your Lordſhips: And they conceive, as to all the Reaſons your Lordſhips have been pleaſed to give them for your Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations, not One of them hath ſo much Argument in them, as they might well expect.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Commons</hi> Reaſon for their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeing to this Amendment, was, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they conceive (that, as they may well infer) from ſo much of their own Vote, as your Lordſhips have
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:49847:39"/>agreed unto, <hi>That King</hi> James <hi>the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond hath Abdicated the Government; and that the Throne is thereby Vacant:</hi> So if they ſhould admit your Lordſhips A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendments, <hi>That he hath only Deſerted the Government;</hi> yet, even thence would follow, <hi>It's Vacant, as to King</hi> James <hi>the Second:</hi> Deſerting the Government be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in true Conſtruction, <hi>Deſerting the Throne.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now, to this they do deſire, That your Lordſhips will conſider and ſee, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you give any Anſwer to this Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; or rather, Whether you do not leave the Matter ſtill in the dark, and (in Truth) leave the Nation in a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual ſtate of War?</p>
                  <p>Your Lordſhips Anſwer to that, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho' you have agreed, that the King has <hi>Deſerted</hi> the Government, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you have made Application to the Prince of <hi>Orange, To take upon him the Adminiſtration of the Government, and thereby provide for the Safety and Peace of the Kingdom;</hi> yet there can be no Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:49847:40"/>drawn from thence, but only that the Exerciſe of the Government by King <hi>James</hi> the Second, was ceaſed, ſo, as the Lords were, and are willing <hi>To Secure the Nation againſt the Return of the ſaid King into this Kingdom;</hi> but not that there was either ſuch an <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication</hi> by him, or <hi>Vacancy</hi> in the Throne, as that the Crown thereby became Elective; to which they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not agree. I deſire now to know of your Lordſhips, what Part of this Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon hath given an Anſwer to what the <hi>Commons</hi> ſaid in their Firſt Reaſon; That they may very well conclude from their own Vote, as to what your Lordſhips have therein agreed to, That <hi>the Throne is Vacant, as to King</hi> James <hi>the Second,</hi> Deſerting the Government, and <hi>Deſerting the Throne,</hi> being in true Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction the ſame. Inſtead of anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Reaſon, your Lordſhips come and apply it here, only to a bare <hi>Giving over the Exerciſe of the Government by King</hi> James. And, pray, my Lords, let us conſider where we are.</p>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:49847:40"/>
                  <p>If the Caſe be ſo, then King <hi>James</hi> the Second, who has only left the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe,</hi> continues in the <hi>Office,</hi> and is King ſtill; and then all the Acts that we have done in this <hi>Convention,</hi> are wholly (as we conceive) not Juſtifiable; You are in no Place or Station to Relieve your ſelves, or the Nation, in this Exigence; unleſs you will think of ſetting up ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Regency by your own Authority, without his Conſent; which, I conceive, by the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> you cannot do.</p>
                  <p>What then follows upon all we have done? We have drawn the Nation into a Snare, by the Steps we have taken; and leave all in ſuch an Intricacy, as we have no Power, by Law, to deliver them out of; nor can we anſwer for what we have done, unleſs the King ſhould dye, and that would leave the Succeſſion uncertain.</p>
                  <p>My Lords, I only apply myſelf to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the Reaſons of your Lordſhips, for inſiſting upon this Second Amendment;
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:49847:41"/>becauſe, I conceive, your Lordſhips have therein given no Anſwer to the Reaſon firſt given by the <hi>Commons,</hi> why they cannot agree to your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> Amendment.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Poll—en.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lords, your own Reaſons (under Favour) do ſhew, That your Lordſhips do intend, that the King is ſtill in the Government? This, I think, is moſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent out of your own Reaſons.</p>
                  <p>For when you have declared, <hi>That the King hath Deſerted the Government,</hi> and then ſay, No Inference can be drawn thence, but only, <hi>That the Exerciſe of the Government by King</hi> James <hi>the Second was Ceaſed;</hi> then you do thereby ſtill ſay, That King <hi>James</hi> the Second is in the Government; for if only <hi>the Exerciſe be Ceaſed,</hi> the <hi>Right</hi> doth ſtill remain: Then, I am ſure, we have no reaſon to Agree with their Lordſhips in that Point.</p>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:49847:41"/>
                  <p>Next, my Lords, truly we cannot ſee how this thing that you would have can be inferred from your own Vote, That <hi>only the Exerciſe of the Government by King</hi> James <hi>ceaſed;</hi> ſince you do not ſay, that he deſerted the Exerciſe of the Government.</p>
                  <p>And if your Lordſhips had any pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to expreſs your Meaning by a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Vote, That <hi>only the Exerciſe ceaſed,</hi> ſurely your Lordſhips would have put in the word <hi>Exerciſe</hi> there: But when in your Vote you ſay, <hi>The Government was deſerted,</hi> you cannot mean only the Exerciſe of it.</p>
                  <p>And that it is the firſt Reaſon that the Commons give your Lordſhips why we cannot by any means admit of your Lordſhips Amendment, becauſe <hi>Throne</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> are in the true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction the ſame; but the Exerciſe of the Government only (as you expreſs it) and the Government it ſelf, (if your Reaſon conclude right) are not the ſame. And we are to reaſon from the words expreſſed in the Vote.</p>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:49847:42"/>
                  <p>Next, my Lords, we ſay. It cannot be inferred from the words, as they reſt in your Lordſhips Vote, that only the Exerciſe of the Government as to King <hi>James</hi> the Second, did ceaſe.</p>
                  <p>For if we read that part about De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting the Government, with the reſt of the Particulars that go before, his endeavouring to Subvert the Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Kingdom, breaking the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Contract, violating the Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Laws, and withdrawing himſelf out of the Kingdom; then can any Man of Underſtanding think that this deſerting of the Government can be any thing elſe but ſomewhat that is agreeable to all thoſe precedent Acts, which are not a ceaſing of the Exerciſe of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment only, but a deſtruction of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment it ſelf.</p>
                  <p>But beſides, my Lords, under Favour, the Adminiſtration or Exerciſe of the Kingly Government is in conſtruction and conſideration of Law all one and the ſame: And, I think, no body that would reaſon aright from thence can
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:49847:42"/>ſay there is any diſtinction between <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> and the <hi>Exerciſe of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment;</hi> for whoſoever takes from the King the <hi>Exerciſe of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> takes from the King his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; for the Power and the Exerciſe of the Power are ſo joyned, that they cannot be ſevered.</p>
                  <p>And the Terms themſelves (taking them as the Law of <hi>England,</hi> which we are to argue from this Caſe, teacheth them) are ſo co-incident, that they cannot either ſubſiſt without conſiſting together: If a Man grant to another the Government of ſuch a Place, this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports the Exerciſe of the Government there to be granted thereby.</p>
                  <p>As if the Iſlands belonging to this Crown and Dominion of <hi>England</hi> (as the Plantations abroad) if the King grants to any one the <hi>Government</hi> of <hi>Jamaica,</hi> or the like, ſure no one will ſay, that That is not a Grant of the Exerciſe of the Government there.</p>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:49847:43"/>
                  <p>So that where-ever a Government is granted, the Exerciſe of that Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is meant and included, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſuppoſed Diſtinction may be ſomething indeed, if they be only no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally conſidered; but it is a Notion altogether diſagreeing to the Laws of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When your Lordſhips ſay in your Reaſons, That <hi>the Exerciſe of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment as to King</hi> James <hi>the Second is ceaſed,</hi> which as far as you can go in this Point, the Commons can by no means agree to this Reaſon; for by the words ſo uſed <hi>(the Exerciſe ceaſed)</hi> we apprehend, that you mean, the Kingſhip continueth ſtill in him, and that only the Exerciſe is gone.</p>
                  <p>And if it be ſo and it be utterly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, and as great a Crime (as what Law ſaith it is not?) to make away from the King the Exerciſe of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, as to take from him the Government, then it may do well for your Lordſhips to conſider, whether
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:49847:43"/>you are not Guilty of the ſame Crime and Thing which you would decline by your Amendment.</p>
                  <p>The Commons therefore cannot ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, That there ſhould be a taking away of the Exerciſe of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from the King, any more than the taking away the Government which (we ſay) he hath himſelf given away by <hi>Abdication.</hi> And if K. <hi>James</hi> be our King ſtill, we cannot by any means agree to the keeping of him out of the Kingdom; for if it be his Right to be King ſtill, God forbid but that he ſhould enjoy it, and be admitted to the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of it again.</p>
                  <p>Then, my Lords, for the Concluſion that your Lordſhips have added to your Reaſon (as making it from the very Words of your Vote) that it is, <hi>That it would infer ſuch a Vacancy in the Throne, as that the Crown ſhould thereby become Elective;</hi> This, we conceive, is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, That he hath no Premiſſes ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from our Actions, or our Sayings, or our Votes, or any thing elſe in this
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:49847:44"/>Caſe; nay, it is quite varying from all the Premiſſes: But when ſuch a Concluſion can be ſhewn to follow from them, then it will be time e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for us to give our Anſwer to it.</p>
                  <p>But, my Lords, this is that we do inſiſt upon; That if the Right of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip be ſtill (after all that is agreed on both hands) due to him, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not in Juſtice agree to keep him from it. And if it be not his due Right, but by theſe Acts, his ſubverſion of the Conſtitution, his breaking the original Contract, and violation of the Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Laws, he hath Abdicated it (as we ſay) and this Abdication hath put him by his Right, and ſo his Right is gone from him (as we conceive it is); then, I think, we may lawfully go on to ſettle the Peace and Welfare of the Nation.</p>
                  <p>But the Right to be ſtill in him to have a Regency upon him without his own Conſent, or till his Return, we take it to be a ſtrange and impracticable thing, and would be introductive of a
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:49847:44"/>new Principle of Government amongſt us. It would be ſetting up a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth inſtead of our ancient re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulated Government, by a limited Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy; then, I am ſure, we ſhould be juſtly blamed: And therefore we can by no means ſubmit to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips Alterations of our Vote, upon any of the Grounds and Reaſons that have as yet been offer'd.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Earl of</hi> C—n.</speaker>
                  <p>As to what Mr. <hi>P—n</hi> hath offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, I deſire to obſerve a word or two, and that is from the Commons ſecond Reaſon for their diſagreeing to their Lordſhips Amendments.</p>
                  <p>You ſay there, That <hi>the Commons do conceive they need not prove to your Lordſhips, that as to any other Perſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides King</hi> James <hi>the Throne is alſo Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant:</hi> Doth not this ſhew, that the meaning of the Vacancy is a Vacancy throughout, as well as with reſpect to King <hi>James.</hi> I ask your Pardon if I do not declare my own Opinion about the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:49847:45"/>Vacancy as to him; but all that I men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion this for, is to know your Meaning in this Point, how far the Vacancy is to extend.</p>
                  <p>You ſaid before, That <hi>He had Abdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated the Government, and thereby the Throne was Vacant.</hi> How is it Vacant? Is it only as to King <hi>James,</hi> or is as to Him and all or any of his Poſterity, or any of thoſe that are in the remainder in the Royal Line in Succeſſion? If it be as to them too, then it muſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily follow, that the Kingdom muſt thereby become Elective ſtill, or the Government changed into a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth; neither of which, we hope, the Commons intend by it. And therefore that made me ask before what a grave and learned Gentleman meant when he ſaid it ſhould not be perpetually Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Mr. Serjeant</hi> M—d.</speaker>
                  <p>I am ſure, if we be left without a Government, as we find we are (why elſe have we deſir'd the Prince to take
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:49847:45"/>upon him the Adminiſtration?) ſure we muſt not be perpetually under Anarchy, the word <hi>Elective</hi> is none of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons word; neither is the making the Kingdom Elective the thing they had in their Thoughts or Intentions; all they mean by this matter, is to provide a Supply for this Defect in the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, brought upon it by the late King's Male Adminiſtration. And I do ſay again, this Proviſion muſt be made; and if it be, that would not make the Kingdom perpetually Elective? I ſtand not upon any Word, but am for the Thing, that a Proviſion be made to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the Defect.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> P—n.</speaker>
                  <p>Do your Lordſhips agree, That the Throne is Vacant as to King <hi>James</hi> the Second? If ſo, or if you will ſay it is full of any body elſe, and will name whom it is full of, it will then be time for the <hi>Commons</hi> to tell what to ſay to it. If your Lordſhips will pleaſe to ſhew that, we ſhall go on to give it an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:49847:46"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Earl of</hi> C—n.</speaker>
                  <p>Your own words in your Second Reaſon are, That <hi>You need not prove to us, that it is to any other Perſon the Throne is alſo Vacant:</hi> Then how ſhould we name who it is full of? Admit for Diſcourſe ſake, but we do not grant it, for my part, I do not. I ſay, taking it to be Vacant, as to King <hi>James</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, then you ask us, Who it ſhould be Supply'd by: Muſt it not be Supply'd by thoſe that ſhould have come if he were dead?</p>
                  <p>For, I pray conſider, I take this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, by all our Laws, to be Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditary Monarchy, and is to go in Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion by Inheritance, in the Royal Line; if then you ſay this Government is Vacant, that would be to put all thoſe by that ſhould take by Succeſſion, and that will make the Kingdom Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive for that time.</p>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:49847:46"/>
                  <p>You ſay, <hi>The Throne is Vacant:</hi> then I may very well ask, Who hath the Right of filling up that Vacancy? We ſay, There is no Vacancy; if there is, pray is there any body that hath the Right of filling it up?</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Mr. Serjeant</hi> M—d.</speaker>
                  <p>That is not the Queſtion before us; yet that will come properly in debate, when we are agreed upon the Vacan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</p>
                  <p>The Noble Lord ſays, <hi>It is by our Law an Hereditary Monarchy.</hi> I grant it; but though it ſhould in an ordinary way deſcend to the Heir, yet as our Caſe is, we have a Maxim in Law as certain as any other, which ſtops the courſe; for no Man can pretend to be King <hi>James</hi>'s Heir while he is living; <hi>Nemo eſt haeres viventis.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:49847:47"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Earl of</hi> P—e.</speaker>
                  <p>To that Point I think my Lord of <hi>C—n</hi> gave an Anſwer, <q rend="margQuotes">That it ſhould go to the next in the Line that were to take it, if the King were dead:</q> for as we ſhould be underſtood, we ſhould make it a Caſe of Demiſe of our Kings, our Law calls it; that is, the King is dead in Law by this <hi>Abdication</hi> or <hi>Deſertion</hi> of the Government, and that the next Heir is to take by Deſcent.</p>
                  <p>You, Gentlemen, ask us who the Throne is full of; I think it is ſufficient to know that there are Heirs who are to take by Lineal Succeſſion, though we do not or cannot poſitively name the particular Perſon; and therefore we may well conclude there is no Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cancy.</p>
                  <p>Suppoſe I ſhould be told ſuch a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman is in ſuch a Room, and there I find him, and another man with him, and I come out and tell you ſo, and ask,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:49847:47"/>
                     <hi>Which is he,</hi> you may be doubtful which of the two is the Man, but ſure the one of them is he; but becauſe you cannot tell which it is, ſhall I conclude no ſuch one is there? If there be a doubtful Title, (that is, dubious in whom the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle reſides, but a certain Title as to ſome one) and I cannot directly name him that hath the immediate Right, yet it is ſufficient to prevent the Vacancy, that there is an Heir or Succeſſor, let him be who he will.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Mr. Serjeant</hi> M—d.</speaker>
                  <p>But your Lordſhips will neither agree it is Vacant, nor tell us how it is Full. King <hi>James</hi> is gone, we hear or know of no other, What ſhall the Nation do in this Uncertainty? When will you tell us who is King, if King <hi>James</hi> be not? Shall we everlaſtingly be in this doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful condition?</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Earl of</hi> P—e.</speaker>
                  <p>Sure Mr. Serjeant <hi>M—d,</hi> you will agree there is One, and no more than
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:49847:48"/>one, to whom a Right does belong of Succeeding, upon failure of King <hi>James.</hi> Has he no Heir known?</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Mr. Serjeant</hi> M—d.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſay, No Man can be his Heir while he lives. If he has any, it is <hi>in Nubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi> our Law knows none; and, What ſhall we do till he be dead? It cannot deſcend till then.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>E. of</hi> P—e.</speaker>
                  <p>You agree, That notwithſtanding King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second was abroad at his Father's Death, and did not actually Exerciſe the Government, yet in Law, immediately upon his Father's Deceaſe, he was not the leſs Heir for that; nor was the Throne Vacant.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Mr. Serjeant</hi> M—d.</speaker>
                  <p>That is not like this Caſe, neither becauſe the Diſcent was Legally imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate; but here can be no ſuch thing du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:49847:48"/>King <hi>James</hi>'s Life, as an Hereditary Diſcent: So that either here muſt be an everlaſting War entail'd upon us, his Title continuing, and we oppoſing his return to the Exerciſe of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, or we have no Government for want of a Legal Diſcent and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion.</p>
                  <p>Pray, my Lords, conſider the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Nation till there be a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; no Law can be executed, no Debts can be compelled to be paid, no Offences can be puniſh'd, no one can tell what to do to obtain his Right, or defend himſelf from Wrong.</p>
                  <p>You ſtill ſay, <hi>The Throne is not Void,</hi> and yet you will not tell us who Fills it: If once you will agree, That <hi>the Throne is Vacant,</hi> it will then come orderly in debate, How it ſhould, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our Law, be Filled.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>E. of</hi> N—m.</speaker>
                  <p>The Objection (as I take it) that is made to theſe Reaſons, the Lords have ſent for their inſiſting upon the Amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:49847:49"/>is, <hi>That we have not fully anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in them the Reaſons given by the Commons for their not agreeing to thoſe Amendments.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> S—l.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lords, we ſay you have not fully anſwered the firſt of our Reaſons.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>E. of</hi> N—m.</speaker>
                  <p>Gentlemen, I intend to ſtate the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection ſo:</p>
                  <p>That firſt Reaſon of yours I take to be this in effect, That our word <hi>(Deſerted)</hi> being apply'd to the Government, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies our Agreeing that the King hath Deſerted the Throne, thoſe two being in true conſtruction the ſame; and then by our own Confeſſion, the Throne is Vacant as to him.</p>
                  <p>To this you ſay, my Lords have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven no Anſwer: Truly, I think it is a clear Anſwer, that the word <hi>(Deſerted)</hi> may have another ſence, and doth not
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:49847:49"/>neceſſarily imply <hi>Renouncing</hi> entirely of a Right, but a ceaſing of the Exerciſe. But then, if that does not Vacant the Throne as to him, the other Reaſon comes to be conſidered, How came you to deſire the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> to take the Adminiſtration upon him, and to take care of <hi>Ireland</hi> till the Conventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to write his Letters circulary for this Meeting? And to renew your Addreſs to the Prince, and to appoint a Day of Publick Thankſgiving?</p>
                  <p>In anſwer to that, my Lords ſay, That tho the King's <hi>Deſerting</hi> the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment (as they agree he has done) did imply the Throne to be Vacant, yet they might juſtly do all thoſe Acts mentioned in the Commons Reaſons; becauſe if barely the Exerciſe of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment were <hi>deſerted,</hi> there muſt be a ſupply of that Exerciſe in ſome Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon's taking the Adminiſtration; and as none ſo fit, becauſe of the Prince's relation to the Crown (and his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence here) to Addreſs unto about it, ſo none ſo proper to make that Addreſs, as the Lords; for in the abſence of the
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:49847:50"/>King they are the King and Kingdoms great Council, and might have done it by themſelves, without the Commons; but being met in a full repreſentative Body, they joyned with them.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>P—n</hi> indeed has ſaid, <hi>There is no diſtinction in Law between the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and the Exerciſe of it.</hi> And That <hi>it is the ſame Crime, in conſideration of Law, to take away the Exerciſe, as to take away the Kingſhip.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I ſhall not diſpute with that learned Gentleman (whom I very much honour for his Knowledge in the Profeſſion of the Law) what Offence either of them would be now, for we are not diſcourſing concerning a Regency, how the Government ſhould be Adminiſtred, but we are barely upon the Queſtion, Whether the Throne be Vacant, ſo that we may have another King. But if we ſhould grant a Vacancy as to the King himſelf, we are then told, the next in Succeſſion cannot take, becauſe no one can be Heir to one that is alive. Yet, I think, the Anſwer given by my Lords
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:49847:50"/>before is a very good one, That <hi>tho the King be not dead Naturally, yet if</hi> (as they infer) <hi>he is ſo Civily, the next of courſe ought to come in as by Heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Succeſſion;</hi> for I know not any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction between Succeſſors in the caſe of a Natural Death, and thoſe in the caſe of a Civil one.</p>
                  <p>For I would know if the next Heir ſhould be ſet aſide in this caſe, and you put in another, whether that King ſhall be King of <hi>England</hi> to him and his Heirs, and ſo being once upon the Throne, the ancient Lineal Succeſſion be altered: If that be ſo, then indeed it is ſufficiently an Elective Kingdom, by taking it from the right Heir.</p>
                  <p>If it be not ſo, then I would ask, Whether ſuch King as ſhall be put in, ſhall be King only during King <hi>James</hi>'s Life. That, I ſuppoſe for many Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, is not their meaning; but, at leaſt he muſt be made King, during his own Life; and then if there be a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction made as to the Succeſſion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a Natural and a Civil Death,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:49847:51"/>if King <hi>James</hi> ſhould dye during the Life of the new King, what would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the Hereditary Monarchy? Where muſt the Succeſſion come in, when the next Heir to King <hi>James</hi> may not be next Heir to the preſent Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor?</p>
                  <p>Therefore we muſt reduce all to this point, which my Lords have hinted at in their Reaſons, Whether this will not make the Kingdom Elective: for if you do once make it Elective, I do not ſay that you are always bound to go to Election, but it is enough to make it ſo, if by that Preſident there be a breach in the Hereditary Succeſſion, for I will be bold to ſay, you cannot make a ſtronger Tye to obſerve that kind of Succeſſion, than what lyeth upon you to preſerve it in this Caſe.</p>
                  <p>If you are under an Obligation to it, it is part of the Conſtitution. I deſire any one to tell me what ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Obligation there can be; and that, I ſay, is Reaſon enough for my Lords
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:49847:51"/>to diſagree to it, it bringing in the Danger of a Breach upon the Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution.</p>
                  <p>Next, Gentlemen, I would know of you, if the Throne be Vacant, whether we be oblig'd to fill it; if we be, we muſt Fill it either by our old Laws, or by the Humour of thoſe that are to chuſe; if we Fill it by our own old Laws, they declare, That it is an Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditary Kingdom, and we are to take the next to whom the Succeſſion would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, and then there would be no need of ſtanding upon a Vacancy.</p>
                  <p>If we are to Fill it according to the Humour of the Times, and of thoſe that are to make the Choice, that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts the courſe of Inheritance, puts it into another Line: And I cannot ſee by what Authority we can do that, or change our Ancient Conſtitution, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out committing the ſame Fault we have laid upon the King.</p>
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:49847:52"/>
                  <p>Theſe are the Objections againſt the Vacancy of the Throne, which occur to me; and We, my Lords, deſire a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to them before we agree to the Vacancy.</p>
                  <p>And, I think, the Anſwering them will lead us unto that which I take to be the main point in queſtion, Whether the Vacancy of the Throne, and Filling it again, will not, as my Lords ſay, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger the turning this Hereditary Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy of ours into an Elective one.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> S—l.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lords, it ſeems very ſtrange to us, that this Queſtion ſhould be asked us, when we come to ſhew, That your Lordſhips Reaſons for leaving out this part of our Vote are not ſatisfactory, neither do anſwer the Reaſons we gave for our not agreeing to your Lordſhips Amendmonts: And it is much ſtranger that we ſhould be asked, Whether this Vacancy extend to the Heirs, when
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:49847:52"/>you will not tell us, whether it be Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant as to King <hi>James</hi> himſelf.</p>
                  <p>You put it upon us to ſay, the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution or Exerciſe of the Government is ceaſed; but you will not ſay the Throne is vacant, ſo much as to him: And if it be not, what have we to do, or conſider, or debate, of any conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, whether it will infer an Election or not?</p>
                  <p>We deſire of your Lordſhips that which we think is very proper; firſt, to know whether the Throne be vacant at all: If it be, then our Propoſition in the concluſion of our Vote is true, That the Throne is thereby vacant.</p>
                  <p>My Lords, I think we come here very much in vain, till this Point be ſetl'd; What Satisfaction can it be to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, or Us, or the Nation, to know that ſuch things as are mentioned in the Votes have been done by King <hi>James,</hi> and that he has deſerted (as you ſay) the Government, if he ſtill retain a Right to it, and your Lordſhips
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:49847:53"/>will not declare he hath no Right, but amuſe the Kingdom with the doubtful words of the <hi>Exerciſe</hi> (as to him) <hi>Cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiug.</hi> If that be all you mean, what need the Queſtion be asked, how far it is va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant, for it ſhould ſeem it is not vacant at all.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>E. of</hi> N—m.</speaker>
                  <p>Will you pleaſe to ſuppoſe it Vacant as to King <hi>James,</hi> that is, that he hath no Right? Then let us go on to the next ſtep.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> S—l.</speaker>
                  <p>That, my Lords, we cannot do, for all our buſineſs is to maintain our own, That the Throne is Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> S—s.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lords, your Lordſhips, as a Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon againſt the word <hi>Abdicate,</hi> ſay, <hi>It is not a word known in our Common Law.</hi> But the word <hi>Vacant,</hi> about which we
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:49847:53"/>are now diſputing, cannot have that Objection made to it; for we find it in our Records, and even apply'd in a parallel Caſe to this of ours, in 1 <hi>Hen.</hi> IV, where it is expreſly made uſe of more than once, and there it doth import what I think it doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port in this Vote of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, now in debate, and to require any further or other Explication of it than the Record gives, will be very hard and unreaſonable; for we are here to give the Commons Reaſons for main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining their own Vote, and nothing elſe.</p>
                  <p>If your Lordſhips pleaſe to look in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Record in that caſe, there was firſt a Reſignation of the Crown and Government made and ſubſcribed by King <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, and this is brought into the Parliament, and there they take notice, that the <hi>Sedes Regalis</hi> (thoſe are the words) <hi>fuit vacua;</hi> and the Reſignation being read both in Latin and in Engliſh, in the Great Hall at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> where the Parliament
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:49847:54"/>was then aſſembled, it was accepted by the Lord's and Commons.</p>
                  <p>After that, it proceeds further; and there are Articles exhibited againſt <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi> the Second, and upon theſe Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles they went on to Sentence of Depoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Deprivation, and then follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the words in the Record; <hi>Et con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſim ut conſtabat ex proemiſſis &amp; eorum occaſione Regnum Angliae cuui pertinentiis ſuis vacare.</hi> Then <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth riſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth up out of his place as Duke of <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caster,</hi> where he ſate before, and ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo high, that he might be well en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ough ſeen, makes this Claim to the Crown: The words in the Record are, <hi>Dictum regnum Angliae ſic ut praemitur Vacans una cum Corona vendicat.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>After that, the Record goeth on, That upon this Claim the Lords and Commons being asked, What they thought of it, they unanimoufly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, and the Archbiſhop took him by the Hand, and led him <hi>ad Sedem Regalem Proedictum, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:49847:54"/>
                  <p>Nay, and after all this, it is there taken notice of, and particularly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved that <hi>prius Vacante ſede Regali,</hi> by the Leaſion and Depoſition aforeſaid all the publick Officers ceaſed; there is care taken for <hi>Hen.</hi> IV's taking the Royal Oath, and granting of new Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions.</p>
                  <p>My Lords, the Commons do there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore apprehend, that with very good Reaſon and Authority they did in their Vote declare the Throne to be Vacant. But as to the going further to enquire into the Conſequences of that, or what is to be done afterwards, is not our Commiſſion, who came here only to maintain their Expreſſions in their Vote againſt your Lordſhips Amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>E. of</hi> R—r.</speaker>
                  <p>In a free Conference the Points in queſtion are freely and fully to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated; and my Lords, in order to their
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:49847:55"/>agreement with the Commons, are to be ſatisfied what is meant, and how far it may extend.</p>
                  <p>You, Gentlemen, that are the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagers for the Houſe of Commons, it ſeems, come with a limited Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and will not enter into that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration which (as our Reaſons ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs) hath a great weight with my Lords, Whether this Vote of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons will not make the Monarchy of <hi>England,</hi> which has always hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore been Hereditary, to become Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive.</p>
                  <p>That the Vacancy of the Throne will infer ſuch a Conſequence, to me appears very plain; And I take it from the Argument that that laſt Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman uſed for the word <hi>Vacant,</hi> out of the Record of <hi>Richard</hi> the Second's time, that is cited for a Preſident for that word. But as that is the only Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident, yet it is attended with this very Conſequence; for it being there declared, That the Royal Seat was
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:49847:55"/>Vacant, immediately did follow an Election of <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, who was not next in the Right Line; Did not then this Hereditary Monarchy in this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance become Elective? When King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second died, I would fain know, whether in our Law the Throne was Vacant. No ſure, the next Heir was immediately in the Throne. And ſo it is in all Hereditary Succeſſive Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments.</p>
                  <p>Indeed, in <hi>Poland,</hi> when the King dyes, there is a Vacancy, becauſe there the Law knows no certain Succeſſor: So that the difference is plain, that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Monarchy is Hereditary, upon the Ceaſing of him in poſſeſſion, the Throne is not Vacant; where it is Elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, 'tis Vacant.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Earl of</hi> C—n.</speaker>
                  <p>I would ſpeak one word to that Record which Mr. <hi>S—s</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, and which the Lord that ſpake
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:49847:56"/>laſt hath given a plain Anſwer unto; by making that difference (which is the great Hinge of the matter in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate) between Hereditary and Elective Kingdoms. But I have ſomething elſe to ſay to that Record.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> It is plain in that Caſe King <hi>Richard</hi> the Second had abſolutely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned, renounced, or (call it what you pleaſe) <hi>Abdicated</hi> in Writing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his own Hand. What is done then? After that, the Parliament be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then ſitting, they did not think it ſufficient to go upon, becauſe that Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting might be the Effect of Fear: And ſo, not voluntary; thereupon they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to a formal Depoſition upon Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, and then comes in the Claim of <hi>Hen.</hi> IV,</p>
                  <p>After all this, Was not this an Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction? He indeed ſaith, That he was not the next Heir, and claimed it by De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent from <hi>Henry</hi> the Third; yet he that was really the next Heir did not appear, which was the Earl of <hi>Maroh;</hi>
                     <pb n="127" facs="tcp:49847:56"/>ſo that <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth claimed it as his indubitable Right, being the next Heir that then appeared.</p>
                  <p>But, Gentlemen, I pray conſider what follow'd upon it; All the Kings that were thus taken in (we ſay Elected, but the Election was not of God's Approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) ſcarce paſſed any one Year in any of their Reigns, without being diſturbed in the poſſeſſion.</p>
                  <p>Yet, I ſay, he himſelf did not care to owe the Crown to the Election, but Claimed it as his Right. And it was a plauſible Pretence, and kept him and his Son (though not without interru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption) upon the Throne. But in the time of his Grandſon <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth, there was an utter Overthrow of all his Title and Poſſeſſion too: For if you look into the Parliament Roll, 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 4. the Proceedings againſt King <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, as well as all the reſt of the Acts during the Uſurpation (as that Record rightly calls it) are annul'd, repeal'd, revok'd, revers'd, and all the
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:49847:57"/>words imaginable uſed and put in, to ſet thoſe Proceedings aſide as illegal, unjuſt, and unrighteous. And, pray what was the Reaſon? That <hi>Act</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth down the Pedigree of the Royal Line, from <hi>Henry</hi> the Third to <hi>Richard</hi> the Second who dy'd without Iſſue, and then <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth (ſaith the Act) Uſurped; but, That the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>March,</hi> upon the Death of <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, and conſequently <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth from him, was undoubted King by Conſcience, by Nature, by Cuſtom, and by Law.</p>
                  <p>The Record is to be ſeen at length, as well as that 1 <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. and being a later Act, is of more Authority.</p>
                  <p>And after all this, (I pray conſider it well) the Right Line is reſtored, and the Uſurpation condemned and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed.</p>
                  <p>Beſides, Gentlemen, I hope you will take into your conſideration, what will become of the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> if
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:49847:57"/>they ſhould differ from us in this Point, and go another way to work, then will that be a divided Kingdom from ours again. You cannot but remember how much Trouble it always gave our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors, while it continued a divided Kingdom; and if we ſhould go out of the Line, and inveſt the Succeſſion in any point at all, I fear you will find a Diſagreement there, and then very dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Conſequences may enſue.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Sir</hi> R—H—d.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lords,</p>
                  <p>The Proceedings and Expreſſions of the Houſe of Commons in this Vote are fully warranted by the Preſident that hath been cited, and are ſuch as where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there has been no interruption of the Government according to the Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution.</p>
                  <p>The late King hath, by your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips conceſſion, done all thoſe things, which amount to an <hi>Abdication</hi> of the
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:49847:58"/>Government, and the Throne's being thereby Vacant: And had your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips concurred with us, the Kingdom had long e're this been ſetled, and every body had peaceably followed their own buſineſs. Nay, had your Lordſhips been pleaſed to expreſs your ſelves clearly, and not had a mind to ſpeak ambiguouſly of it, we had ſaved all this Trouble, and been at an end of Diſputing.</p>
                  <p>Truly, my Lords, this Record that hath been mentioned of <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, I will not ſay is not a Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of Election, for the Arch-Biſhop ſtood up, and looked round on all ſides, and asked the Lords and Commons, <hi>Whether they would have him to be King;</hi> and they aſſerted, (as the words of the Roll are) That <hi>He ſhould Reign over them.</hi> And ſo it is done at every Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation.</p>
                  <p>As to his Claim, they did not ſo much mind that, for they knew that he Claimed by Deſcent and Inheritance,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:49847:58"/>when there was a known Perſon that had a Title before him.</p>
                  <p>For, that which a Noble Lord ſpoke of touching the Publick Acts that have been done ſince the King left us, I may very well ſay, we think them legally done; and we do not doubt but that Power which brought in another Line then, upon the Vacancy of the Throne by the Leaſion of <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, is ſtill, according to the Conſtitution, reſiding in the Lords and Commons, and is legally ſufficient to ſupply the Vacancy that now is.</p>
                  <p>That Noble Lord indeed ſaid, That your Lordſhips might not only with the Commons adviſe the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> to take upon him the Adminiſtration, and joyn with us in the other things, but that you might have done it of your ſelves, as being in the abſence of the King, the Great Council of the Nation.</p>
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:49847:59"/>
                  <p>My Lords,</p>
                  <p>I ſhall not ſay much to that point, your Lordſhips Honours Privileges are great, and your Councils very worthy of all Reverence and Reſpect.</p>
                  <p>But I would ask this Queſtion of any Noble Lord that is here, Whether, had there been an Heir, to whom the Crown had quietly deſcended in the Line of Succeſſion, and this Heir certainly known, your Lordſhips would have aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembl'd without his calling, or would have either Adminiſter'd the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment your ſelves, or adviſed the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> to have taken it upon him? I doubt you had been (pardon me to ſay it) all guilty of High-Treaſon, by the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> if a known Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor were in poſſeſſion of the Throne, as he muſt be if the Throne were not Vacant.</p>
                  <p>From thence, my Lords, your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips ſee where the Difficulty lyes in this matter, and whence it ariſeth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:49847:59"/>you would not agree the Throne to be Vacant when we know of none that poſſeſs it.</p>
                  <p>We know ſome ſuch thing hath been pretended to as an Heir Male, of which there are different Opinions, and in the mean time, we are without a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and, Muſt we ſtay till the Truth of the matter be found out? What ſhall we do to preſerve our Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, while we are without a ſafe or legal Authority to act under the ſame according to that Conſtitution, and in a little time it will, perhaps, through the diſtraction of our Conſtitution, be utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly irremediable?</p>
                  <p>I do not deny, but that your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips have very great Hardſhips to conflict with in ſuch a Caſe, but who is the occaſion of them?</p>
                  <p>We all do know the Monarchy is Hereditary; but how, or what ſhall we do to find out the Succeſſor in the Right Line?</p>
                  <pb n="134" facs="tcp:49847:60"/>
                  <p>You think it will be a difficult thing to go upon the Examination who is Heir; perhaps it will be more difficult to Reſolve in this Caſe, than it might be in another: For though heretofore there have been <hi>Abdications</hi> and <hi>Vacan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,</hi> it has been where the King has been of the ſame Religion of the Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd Worſhip of the Nation; and amongſt thoſe that pretended to the Succeſſion, the ſeveral Claimers have been Perſons born and bred up in that Religion that was Eſtabliſh'd by Law; or it may be there hath been a Child in the Womb at the time of the Vacancy.</p>
                  <p>But then, my Lords, there would not be much difficulty to examine, Who ſhould Inherit, or what were fit to be done. I confeſs, I ſay, there are Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of all ſides, or elſe your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips ſure would have ſpoke out before now: And if you had been clear in it your ſelves, you would have let the Commons and the World have known
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:49847:60"/>it. But it not being clear, muſt we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways remain thus? Uſe what words you will, <hi>Fill up,</hi> or <hi>Nominate,</hi> or <hi>Elect,</hi> it is the thing we are to take care of, and it is high time it were done.</p>
                  <p>My Lords,</p>
                  <p>There is no ſuch Conſequence to be drawn from this Vote, as an Intention or a Likelihood of altering the Courſe of the Government, ſo as to make it Elective, the Throne hath all along de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended, in an Hereditary Succeſſion, the main Conſtitution hath been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved.</p>
                  <p>The Preſident of <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth is not like that of Elections in other Countries; and I am ſorry there ſhould be any occaſion for what is neceſſary to be done now.</p>
                  <p>But when ſuch Difficulties are upon the Nation, that we cannot extricate our ſelves out of, as to the Lineal Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor, your Lordſhips, I hope, will give
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:49847:61"/>us leave to remember <hi>Salus populi eſt Suprema Lex.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And if neither You nor we can do any thing in this Caſe, We, who are met under the Notion of an Aſſembly or Convention of the States, then have met to no purpoſe; for after we have Voted our ſelves to be without a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, (which looks as if ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing were really intended as to a Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement) all preſently ſinks, and we are as much in the dark as we were before.</p>
                  <p>And, my Lords, I pray give me leave to ſay one thing more: Your Lordſhips ſay, You will never make a Preſident of Election, or take upon you to Alter the Succeſſion.</p>
                  <p>With your Lordſhips Favour, the Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement of the Conſtitution is the main thing we are to look after. If you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for the ſupply of the Defect there, that point of the Succeſſion will, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all queſtion, in the ſame method,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:49847:61"/>and at the ſame time be ſurely provided for.</p>
                  <p>But, my Lords, you will do well to conſider; Have not you your ſelves al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready limited the very Succeſſion, and cut off ſome that might have a Line at Right? Have you not concurred with us in our Vote, <hi>That it is inconſiſtent with our Religion and our Laws to have a Papist to Reign over us?</hi> Muſt we not come then to an Election, if the next Heir be a Papiſt? Nay, ſuppoſe there were no Proteſtant Heir at all to be found, would not your Lordſhips then break the Line?</p>
                  <p>By your Lordſhips Vote that is ſo inconſiſtent, you do ſuppoſe a Caſe of the greateſt Conſequence that can be, may happen; and if that ſhould hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to be our Caſe, that the whole Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Line ſhould fail, would not that neceſſitate an Election, or elſe we muſt ſubmit to that which were inconſiſtent with our Religion and our Laws?</p>
                  <pb n="138" facs="tcp:49847:62"/>
                  <p>If your Lorſhips then, in ſuch a Caſe, muſt break through the Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, I think the Nation has reaſon to expect you ſhould take care to ſupply the preſent Defect, where the Succeſſion is uncertain.</p>
                  <p>My Lords,</p>
                  <p>If this ſhould not be agreed unto, what will be the Conſequence? We that uſed, and juſtly, to boaſt of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving under the Beſt of Governments, muſt be left without any one; for, your Lordſhips, it ſeems, cannot agree with us to ſupply and Fill up this Gap in it, or tell us who is the Succeſſor: And we muſt not do it our ſelves by E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection; which is the only way left us to provide for our Settlement.</p>
                  <p>Truly my Lords, upon the whole, I cannot tell what condition we ſhall be in, or what we can do further; but we muſt even part, and break up in Confuſion, and ſo leave the Nation to extricate it ſelf, as well as it can, out
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:49847:62"/>of this Diſtraction. But then, at whoſe Door that will lye, I muſt leave to your Lordſhips own Thoughts.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>E. of</hi> P—e.</speaker>
                  <p>We have indeed paſſed ſuch a Vote, as that Gentleman ſays, againſt a <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh</hi> Prince's reigning over us, but I ſhould think that amounts to no more than a Reſolution, that by a Law to be made we will take care of it in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament: Therefore I think that which we aim at, and that which the Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of our Gouernment does require, is, to put things in a legal method: And, in order to it, I would have the Legal Succeſſor declared and proclaimed, and then a Parliament ſummoned in that Prince's Name, and the whole matter ſetled there.</p>
                  <p>An Act made by a King <hi>de facto</hi> is Void as to a King <hi>de jure;</hi> therefore I would have the Conſtitution preſerved, and would deſire, that all that is done
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:49847:63"/>in this matter may be again done in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>E. of</hi> C—n.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir <hi>R—H—d</hi> was pleas'd to ſay, That <hi>by the ſame method that the Throne now ſhould be Filled, by the ſame the Succeſſor ſhould be D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>clared, and the Right Line Setled.</hi> Is not that declaring the Crown to be Elective?</p>
                  <p>Suppoſe you ſay nothing, but Fill the Throne, Is it not to take away the Right Line of Inheritance? And, Will not ſuch Succeſſor claim it for his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity?</p>
                  <p>Truly, I think if the Right Line be Declared in the ſame way that the Succeſſor is, then we take upon us to diſpoſe of the Inheritance of the Crown abſolutely; which, I think, by all the Law I ever read or could hear of among us, is out of our Power; and, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Houſe, or both Houſes together,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:49847:63"/>have power to do any thing relating to the Succeſſion, but by Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; which the two Houſes by them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>ſelves cannot make.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Sir</hi> R.—T—e.</speaker>
                  <p>I think we are now going too far in this matter; the Queſtion before us is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Whether there be a Vacancy in the Throne.</hi> After we have done with that, I do not ſee how this will preclude the conſideration of any Claim to the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion.</p>
                  <p>Your Lordſhips ſay, <hi>You are under great Difficulties upon this Subject.</hi> But, my Lords, till you have declared the Throne Vacant, I muſt preſume to ſay, I do not ſee how it is poſſible for any of us to make one ſtep towards a Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p>If there be any Claims to the Crown, that conſideration will be next; and how to come at them, I conceive we
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:49847:64"/>are in the ſame Capacity as our Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors were to provide for all Exigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies as ſhall emerge, and for the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying all Defects in the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p>It is true, by the Acts of Queen <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth</hi> and King <hi>James,</hi> firſt, we have the Oaths of Supremacy and Allegiance that are to be, and have been taken by all Perſons.</p>
                  <p>But, my Lords, there is an old Oath of Fidelity, that uſeth to be required in Leets, and that by the ancient Law of <hi>England</hi> every man ought to take that is Sixteen Years of Age; and this was as much obliging to the King, his Heirs and Succeſſors, as any of thoſe later Oaths are, for they ſeem only to be made to exclude foreign Authorities, and not to infer any new Obedience or Subjection; therefore I am only ſaying, we are in as natural a capacity as any of our Predeceſſors were to provide for a Remedy in ſuch Exigencies as this.</p>
                  <pb n="143" facs="tcp:49847:64"/>
                  <p>I do not intend to trouble your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips any farther than the words of the Vote lead me.</p>
                  <p>If the Throne were Full, what do we do here; nay, how came we hither? I would fain know, whether all that is mention'd in one of our Reaſons of the Adminiſtration being committed to the Prince, and thoſe other Acts, do not all imply at leaſt that we are in ſuch a Caſe as <hi>wherein the Throne is Vacant,</hi> otherwiſe, if it had been full, I appeal to any one, whether we could have aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled or acted in any other Name, or by an other Authority, than his that filled it. Then do not all theſe things declare, that there is a Vacan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy?</p>
                  <p>My Lords,</p>
                  <p>I have done, having ſaid this, That it is a ſubſequent conſideration, how the Throne ſhall be Filled, and all the Particulars that relate to it remain entire, after this Reſolution taken.</p>
                  <pb n="144" facs="tcp:49847:65"/>
                  <p>But I think we are at preſent to go no further. No Man, I hope, thinks there is a juſt Ground for any Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of an Intention to change the Government; I am ſure there is no Ground for any ſuch Apprehenſion: So that we have all the reaſon in the World ſtill to inſiſt, That your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips ſhould agree with us, that the Throne is Vacant, or we ſhall not be able to move one ſtep further towards a ſettlement.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Sir</hi> T—L—e.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lords,</p>
                  <p>So much has been ſaid in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter already, that very little is to be added.</p>
                  <p>But give me leave to ſay unto your Lordſhips, That thoſe Amendments your Lordſhips have made to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons Vote, are not agreeing with your other Votes, nor any of the Acts done
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:49847:65"/>ſince the <hi>Abdication.</hi> Had it been in the common ordinary caſe of a Vacancy by the King's Death, your Lordſhips in <hi>December</hi> laſt would ſure have let us know as much: But it is plain you were ſenſible we were without a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, by your deſiring the Prince to take the Adminiſtration, and to iſſue out his Letters from this Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>But, my Lords, I would ask this Queſtion, whether upon the original Contract there were not a power pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in the Nation to provide for its ſelf in ſuch Exigencies?</p>
                  <p>That contract was to ſettle the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution as to the Legiſlature which a noble Lord in the beginning ſpoke of; ſo we take it to be: And it is true, that it is a part of the Contract, the making of the Laws, and that thoſe Laws ſhould oblige all ſides when made; but yet ſo, as not to exclude this origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal conſtitution in all Governments that commence by compact, that there
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:49847:66"/>ſhould be a Power in the States to make proviſion in all times, and upon all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, for extraordinary Caſes and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities, ſuch as ours now is.</p>
                  <p>I ſay nothing now as to the Heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Succeſſion; our Government has been always taken to be Hereditary, and ſo declared when there has been occaſion to make proviſion otherwiſe than in the direct Line.</p>
                  <p>But our matter is ſingly upon a Point of Fact, Whether the Throne be Vacant (as the Commons ſay it is) by the <hi>Abdication</hi> of King <hi>James</hi> the Second.</p>
                  <p>This preſent Vacancy is neareſt to that of <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, of any that we meet with in our Records; and the Phraſe being there uſed, we inſiſt upon it as very proper. And when that is agreed unto, the Houſe will, no doubt, declare their Minds in another Conſequential Queſtion that
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:49847:66"/>ſhall ariſe in a Proper way. But this is all we can ſpeak to now.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Sir</hi> G—T—y.</speaker>
                  <p>To diſcourſe, Whether the Crown of <hi>England</hi> would by this means become Elective, is altogether unneceſſary; and I think your Lordſhips have given no Reaſons that are ſufficient to make the Objection out, neither any Anſwers to the Commons Reaſons for their Vote.</p>
                  <p>It ſeems to me an odd way of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning, firſt to miſtake the meaning, and then give Reaſons againſt that mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken meaning.</p>
                  <p>The Queſtion is only here, Whether we can make good this Propoſition, <hi>That the Throne is Vacant by the Abdica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of tht late King.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="148" facs="tcp:49847:67"/>
                  <p>I confeſs, 'tis a melancholy thing to diſcourſe of the Miſcarriages of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but 'tis much more afflictive to talk of unhinging all the Monarchy by a breach upon the direct Line of the Succeſſion, as, if the Crown of <hi>England</hi> did actually deſcend to <hi>Lewis</hi> the Four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth, it would not be in the power of the States of this Kingdom to divolve it upon another Head,</p>
                  <p>A Noble Lord put an Inſtance of two Men in one Room, one of whom was really ſuch a one: But though a ſtander by could not directly tell which was he, yet it could not be ſaid by him, that ſuch a one was not there. But if you pleaſe, I will put this Caſe:</p>
                  <p>Suppoſe there were two Men in one Room, that no one alive could tell which was which; as ſuppoſe this to be the Caſe of the two Children of <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth, that they had been kept cloſe Priſoner by their Uncle <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi>
                     <pb n="149" facs="tcp:49847:67"/>the Third, ſo long, that there were no living Witneſſes able to tell which was the eldeſt of the two, that would occaſion a difficulty much what as intricate as ours here. One of them muſt be Eldeſt, but by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the uncertainty, muſt not an Election be made of them? And, could any thing elſe do but an Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction?</p>
                  <p>But, I ſay, the proper ſingle Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on here is, Whether we have well ſaid, and well affirmed upon the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes that are mentioned in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer part of the Vote, that he was <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated,</hi> and that the Throne is thereby Vacant.</p>
                  <p>Your Lordſhips in part agree; for you ſay, <hi>He has Deſerted the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> then you ſay, <hi>He is not in it.</hi> And it is as much as to ſay, He has left the Kingdom deſtitute of a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</p>
                  <pb n="150" facs="tcp:49847:68"/>
                  <p>Now, if there be any ſence in which our Propoſition is true, will you deny the whole Propoſition, becauſe it may be taken in a ſence that is dubious and uncertain, as to the Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
                  <p>You cannot ſay the Throne is Full; if then there be a Doubt with you, to be ſure it is not like to be evident to us, eſpecially in this Caſe, conſidering who your Lordſhips are.</p>
                  <p>You are the Perſons that uſually are or ought to be preſent at the Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of our Queens, and the proper Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes to the Birth of our Princes. If then your Lordſhips had known who was on the Throne, we ſhould certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have heard his Name from you, and that had been the beſt Reaſon againſt the Vacancy as could have been given.</p>
                  <pb n="151" facs="tcp:49847:68"/>
                  <p>My Lords,</p>
                  <p>We ſay no more than our Anceſtors have ſaid before us, as you ſee by the Parliament-Roll, 1 <hi>Henry</hi> IV; and I muſt maintain the Record to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that the Government is Vacant, as it is there declared, and as it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in our Vote: So that we have not invented or coined a word for our turn, neither is the Notion new, it is a word that has been uſed before in a Caſe as near this as any can be<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>But it is objected, that That ſhould be no Preſident, becauſe of what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd upon that Vacancy of the Throne. I deſire that your Lornſhips would read the Record.</p>
                  <p>The next thing there, is, <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth cometh himſelf, and ſays, <hi>He Claimed the Crown as deſcended from</hi> Henry <hi>the Third, and the Lords and Commons aſſented.</hi> It is true, the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop did propoſe him (as was uſual at Coronations) and he did there
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:49847:69"/>actually ask them, <hi>Whether they did chuſe him for their King;</hi> they agreed to it, and the Arch-Biſhop makes a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe upon the Virtues of a Man to Govern the Nation better than a Child; and then he is placed in the Throne. And this I take to be a proper, plain, applicable Preſident in our Caſe.</p>
                  <p>But that Noble Lord's Objection ſtrikes at the very Heart of it, if the Objection be rightly made, That all theſe Proceedings, and ſo conſequently the Words and Phraſes there uſed, are all repealed, 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 4.</p>
                  <p>My Lords,</p>
                  <p>It is very well known, and readily agreed by us, that <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth came in in diſaffirmance of the Title of the Houſe of <hi>Lancaſter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As thoſe times went, whenever there was any Turn in Government, (as there were ſeveral) there were new and contrary Declarations about the Title to the Crown, made conſtantly in
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:49847:69"/>Parliament; and what one Parliament ſetled, another undid.</p>
                  <p>But then this Advantage we have on our ſide, that as we have this firſt Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident for us, ſo we have the laſt; for I need go no farther than the Parliament Roll of 1 <hi>Henry</hi> VII. 12.16. where the Record is ſet right again.</p>
                  <p>The Act for Depoſing <hi>Richard</hi> the Second is indeed by 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> IV. Repeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſaith, That <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth uſurped the Crown, and murder'd <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi> the Second; and thereupon it proceeds to attaint <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth. But then comes in <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh, and 1 <hi>Henry</hi> VII. there is an Act made, that ſets aſide all the Acts and Attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders made againſt his Line, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently repealed 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> IV, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed 1 <hi>Hen.</hi> IV.</p>
                  <p>And I would obſerve one thing by the way concerning <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth: He was of the Line of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> and when he came to the Crown, would
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:49847:70"/>not endure to have his Crown reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed only Matrimonial, or ſuffer the Stile to go in the Names of <hi>Henry</hi> and <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> as he muſt have done if he had ſtuck to the Title by the Right Line of Succeſſion: No, he always ſtood up for his own Title, though he had the Hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſs of the Houſe of <hi>York</hi> in his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom.</p>
                  <p>Therefore, my Lords, his Act for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring the Record of 1 <hi>Henry</hi> IV. again, it is as good an Authority as it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and ſomewhat better; for it hath the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> on its ſide, which is unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed to this day.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>E. of</hi> P—e.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh had a good Right and Title by Marriage to the Crown, <hi>in re <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xoris.</hi> No one can queſtion but his own Title, as deſcended from <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the Fourth, was an Uſurpation; and he would not ſuffer any one to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:49847:70"/>which Title was beſt, as long as it was acknowledg'd he had one good one</p>
                  <p>That this Kingdom is Hereditary we are not to prove by Preſident in the Liſt of our Kings and Queens; for we ſhall ſcarce find above three in any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect Line, without ſome interruption; and therefore we are not to fetch our Preſidents or Proofs ſo far as thoſe days. And this I ſpeak for the Reaſon which was hinted before.</p>
                  <p>The Laws made are certainly part of the Original Contract; and by the Laws made, which eſtabliſh the Oath of Allegiance and Supremacy, we are ty'd up to keep in the Hereditary Line, being ſworn to be true and faithful to the King, his Heirs and Succeſſors; whereas the old Oath was, only to bear true Allegiance to the King. There (I take it) lies the Reaſon why we cannot (of our ſelves) without break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Contract, break the Succeſſion, which is ſetled by a Law, and cannot
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:49847:71"/>be altered but by another, which we our ſelves cannot make.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Sir</hi> G— T—y.</speaker>
                  <p>Your Lordſhip is pleaſed to ſay <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the Seventh's Title by Deſcent was an Uſurpation. I think it is pretty hard to determine what Title he did govern by, ſince though his Wife was the Lineal Heir, yet ſhe had no part, or ſo much as a Name in the Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And if it were too great an Iſſue to be try'd then, it will be harder to do it now. And it has been ſaid, It was his Mother's Counſel to him, not to declare particularly upon what Foot his Title ſtood.</p>
                  <p>But, my Lords, if we ſhould allow none for Acts of Parliament, but thoſe that were made in the Reigns of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditary Kings, and in the Right Line, I doubt we ſhould want the greateſt part of thoſe Laws that compoſe the Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:49847:71"/>of Statute-Books, and the Records by which we enjoy a great part of our Inheritances and Poſſeſſions.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Mr. Serjeant</hi> M—d</speaker>
                  <p>If we look but into the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true (that is above all Humane Laws) we have enough to juſtify us in what we are now a doing, to provide for our ſelves and the Publick Weal in ſuch an Exigency as this.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Sir</hi> R—T—e.</speaker>
                  <p>If Laws made about the Succeſſion be ſo obliging, what then ſhall we ſay to the Succeſſion of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> who had an Act of Parliament (to the keeping of which an Oath was requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) againſt both her and her Siſter.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <pb n="158" facs="tcp:49847:72"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>E. of</hi> P—e.</speaker>
                  <p>But to ſhew what Opinion ſhe her ſelf and the Wiſe Men of her Times had, and were of, in this point, there is an Act, made in her Reign, and yet in being, which declares it to be a <hi>Proemunire</hi> to affirm, The Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment cannot ſettle the Succeſſion of the Crown, or alter it. Entails in Parliament have been of the Crown, both ancient and modern, yet the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of another ſubſequent Act has prevail'd againſt ſuch an Entail: So that it ſhould be done, I ſay, in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Sir</hi> R—T—e</speaker>
                  <p>I think we are in as full a Capacity to take care of the Government as any of our Predeceſſors, in ſuch an Exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence; and if we do as they have done
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:49847:72"/>before us, that is not to be called a changing of the Monarchy from an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditary to an Elective.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>E. of</hi> N—m.</speaker>
                  <p>After this long Debate, pray let us endeavour to come as near as we can to an Agreement: We have propoſed ſome Queſtions, about which my Lords deſired to be ſatisfied; You, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, have not been pleaſed to give an Anſwer to them, and we have no great Hopes of getting one from you, as this Debate ſeems to be mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</p>
                  <p>On your part, you have declared, That you do acknowledge the Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy is Hereditary and Succeſſive in the Right Line; then I cannot ſee how ſuch an Acknowledgment conſiſts with the Reaſons you give for your Vacancy; for I cannot imagine how a Kingdom can be an Hereditary Kingdom, and that King who hath Children now in
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:49847:73"/>being (at the time of his forſaking the Government) can have the Throne Vacant both of him and his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
                  <p>The Courſe of Inheritance, as to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> is, by our Law, a great deal better provided for, and runs ſtronger in the right Line of Birth than of any other Inheritance. No Attainder of the Heir of the Crown will bar the Succeſſion to the Throne, as it doth the Deſcent to any common perſon. The very Deſcent, by Order of Birth, will take away any ſuch De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</p>
                  <p>And ſo was the Opinion of the great Lawyers of <hi>England,</hi> in the Caſe of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh. Then cannot I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend how any Act of the Father's can bar the Right of the Child (I do not mean that an Act of Parliament cannot do it); I never ſaid ſo, nor thought ſo, but I ſay, no Act of the Father's alone can do it, ſince even the Act of the Son, which may endanger
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:49847:73"/>an Attainder in him, cannot do it, ſo careful is the Law of the Royal Line of Succeſſion. This is declar'd by many Acts of Parliament, and very fully and particularly by that Statute 25 <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, <hi>Cap.</hi> 22, entituled, <hi>An Act concerning the King's Succeſſion;</hi> where the Succeſſion of the Crown is limited to the King's Iſſue-Male firſt, then Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male, and the Heirs of their Bodies one after another, by courſe of Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, according to their Ages, as the Crown of <hi>England</hi> hath been accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and ought to go in ſuch Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
                  <p>If then the King hath done any thing to diveſt himſelf of his own Right, it doth not follow thence, that That ſhall exclude the Right of his Iſſue; and then the Throne is not Vacant, as long as there are any ſuch Iſſue; for no Act of the Father can Vacant for himſelf and Children.</p>
                  <pb n="162" facs="tcp:49847:74"/>
                  <p>Therefore if you mean no more than but the diveſting his own Right, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired you would declare ſo: And then ſuppoſe the Right gone as to him, yet if it deſcend to his Lineal Succeſſor, it is not Vacant.</p>
                  <p>And I told you, One Reaſon my Lord's did ſtand upon againſt agreeing to the Vacancy, was, Becauſe they thought your Vote might extend a great deal further than the King's own Perſon.</p>
                  <p>But your all owning it to be a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neal Inheritance, and this Vacancy, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks, do not by any means con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt.</p>
                  <p>You declare, you never meant to alter the Conſtitution; then you muſt preſerve the Succeſſion in its ancient courſe: So I did hear a worthy Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman conclude it to be your Intention to do. But by what methods can it be done in this Caſe by us? I deſire to be
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:49847:74"/>ſatisfied in a few things about this very matter.</p>
                  <p>I deſire firſt to know, Whether the Lords and Commons have Power by themſelves to make a binding Act or Law. And then I deſire to know, Whether according to our ancient Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Conſtitution every King of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> by being ſeated on the Throne, and poſſeſſed of the Crown, is not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by King, to him and his Heirs. And without an Act of Parliament, (which we alone cannot make) I know not what Determination we can make of his Eſtate.</p>
                  <p>It has been urged indeed, That we have in Effect already agreed to what is contain'd in this Vote, by Voting, That it is inconſiſtent with our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Laws to have a <hi>Popiſh Prince</hi> to Rule over us.</p>
                  <pb n="164" facs="tcp:49847:75"/>
                  <p>But I would fain know, Whether they that urge this, think that the Crown of <hi>Spain</hi> is Legally and Actual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly excluded from the Succeſſion by this Vote.</p>
                  <p>No Man ſure will undertake to tell me, That Vote of either Houſe, or both Houſes together, can Alter the Law in this or any other point.</p>
                  <p>But becauſe I am very deſirous that this Vote ſhould have its Effect, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that every thing of this Nature ſhould be done in the antient uſual Method, by Act of Parliament.</p>
                  <p>GOD forbid that ſince we are hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily deliver'd from the Fears of <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary Power,</hi> we ſhould aſſume any ſuch Power to our ſelves; What Advantage ſhould we then give to thoſe who would quarrel with our Settlement for the Illegality of it? Would not this, which we thus endeavour to cruſh, break forth into a Viper?</p>
                  <pb n="165" facs="tcp:49847:75"/>
                  <p>For that Record of 1. <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, I acknowledge the words of the Royal Seat being Vacant are us'd. But ſince you your ſelves tell us of it, That <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth did claim by Inheritance from his Grandfather, that, methinks, may come up to what I would have the declared ſence of both Houſes upon this Queſtion; (to wit) The Throne might be Vacant of <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, but not ſo Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant but the claim of the immediate Succeſſor was to take place, and not be excluded, but entirely preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
                  <p>And <hi>Richard</hi> the Second ſeems to have had the ſame Opinion, by delivering over his Signet to them.</p>
                  <p>Our Laws know no <hi>Inter regnum;</hi> but upon the Death of the Predeceſſor the next Heir is <hi>in uno &amp; eodem in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanti.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="166" facs="tcp:49847:76"/>
                  <p>It was ſo Reſolv'd even in <hi>Richard</hi> the Second's own Caſe; for at his Grandfather's Death it was a Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Whether King <hi>Richard</hi> the Second or the Eldeſt Son of his Grandfather, then living, ſhould ſucceed; and it was Reſolved, That he ought to have it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of his Right of Inheritance; which is the more remarkable, becauſe of the conteſt.</p>
                  <p>And when <hi>Richard</hi> the Third uſurped his Crown, to make his Claim good to the Right of Inheritance, he Baſtardiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his own Nephews.</p>
                  <p>And ſo it was in all the Inſtances of the Breaches that were made upon the Line of Succeſſion, which were ſome Seven (but all illegal); for ſuch was the Force of the Laws, that the Uſurpers would not take the Crown upon them, unleſs they had ſome ſpecious pretence of an Hereditary Title to it.</p>
                  <pb n="167" facs="tcp:49847:76"/>
                  <p>That which I would have Avoided by all means, is, the Miſchievous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences that I fear will enſue upon this Vacancy of the Throne, (to wit) the utter Overthrow of the whole Coſtitution of our Government. For if it be ſo, and the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons only remain as parts of it, Will not this make the King one of the Three Eſtates? Then is he the Head of the Commonwealth, all united in one Body under him. And if the Head be taken away, and the Throne Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant, by what Laws or Conſtitutions is it that we retain Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons? For they are knit together in their common Head; and if one part of the Government be diſſolved, I ſee not any Reaſon but that all muſt be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved.</p>
                  <p>Therefore 'tis of very great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance that we come to an Explana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, how far you mean the Throne to be Vacant; and that if it reach to the King and his Heirs, (notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:49847:77"/>all the the Acts of Parliament about the Succeſſion) we may conſider how the conſequences of that will effect the Conſtitution; for, I preſume to ſay, it may then be in your power as well as to ſay, we ſhall have no King at all.</p>
                  <p>I was miſtaken by the Gentlemen who took notice of what I ſaid the Lords might do of themſelves, in the abſence of the King: I would not be underſtood to ſay, the Government devolved upon the Lords; but I may ſay they are the Governments great Council in the interval of Parliaments, and may have greater ſway by the Privilege of their <hi>Birth,</hi> in the Exigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the State: As appears in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Inſtances, and particularly the firſt of <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth, and during his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy.</p>
                  <p>There was a Caſe put by one Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, about the two Sons of <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth, being kept Priſoners ſo long, till it could not be known by
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:49847:77"/>any Living Witneſſes which was the Eldeſt: I would only ask that Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, Whether in that caſe he would ſay the Throne were Vacant; certainly there would have been One in the Throne.</p>
                  <p>But then it followeth, that though there ſhould be an Uncertainty of the particular Perſon, yet that would not infer a Neceſſity that the Throne ſhould be Vacant.</p>
                  <p>Upon the whole matter, you ſeem to underſtand your own words to ſignifie leſs than they do really im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port.</p>
                  <p>I do not find that you purpoſe to make the Kingdom Elective; and yet you talk of ſupplying the Vacancy by the Lords and Commons.</p>
                  <p>You do not ſay, That the King has left the Crown for himſelf and his Heirs; and yet your words ſpeak of a Vacancy, and nothing of the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion;
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:49847:78"/>but you do not tell us what you mean.</p>
                  <p>Therefore, if this matter were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, that my Lords may know how far the Intention of the Vote reacheth, that it may not abroad, or hereafter, be conſtrued to go beyond ſuch Meaning, (that is) as to the King himſelf, and not to his Heirs, perhaps there might quickly be a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pier Accommodation than can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected while things remain thus, ſtill in doubt, and in the dark.</p>
                  <p>Gentlemen,</p>
                  <p>If any of you can ſettle this Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in its true Light, it would do very well; and it is You muſt do it; for the Words are Yours, and ſo we muſt be told your Signification and Intention by your ſelves.</p>
                  <p>If you mean by <hi>Abdication</hi> and <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cancy</hi> only that the King has <hi>left the Government,</hi> and it is Devolved upon the next Succeſſor, that may perhaps
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:49847:78"/>ſatisfie my Lords, and we may agree upon ſome Settlement.</p>
                  <p>I muſt confeſs, any Government is better than none; but I earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſire we may enjoy our Ancient Conſtitution.</p>
                  <p>Therefore I again renew my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, That you would come to ſuch an Explanation as may breed an U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion between the two Houſes, for the ſtrength of your Conſultation and Reſolutions in this great Emergency.</p>
                  <p>If the Kingdom were indeed Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive, we were in a Capacity of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting, but <hi>pro hac Vice,</hi> according to the Conſtitution, this Queſtion would be greater than what it was before; but then the great Debate in it would only be, Who ſhould firſt have the Honour of Laying the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Foundation of the New Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p>But as this caſe ſtands upon the Foot of our Ancient Laws, and Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:49847:79"/>conſtitution, I humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you to conſider, Whether at the ſame time that in this way you get an Eſtabliſh'd Government, you do not overturn all our Legal Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> P—F—y.</speaker>
                  <p>I hope, my Lords, there is no danger of ſhaking our Fundamentals in this caſe; but we are purſuing thoſe Methods that agree with our Laws and Conſtitution: For though the Monarchy of this Nation be He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditary in the Ordinary courſe of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, yet there may fall out a caſe wherein that cannot be comply'd with, and a plain Vacancy may enſue. For, put the caſe the whole Royal Lines ſhould fail, (as they are all mortal as well as we our ſelves are) ſhould we in that caſe have no Goveenment at all? And, who then ſhould we have but the Lords &amp; Commons? and I think that caſe comes neareſt to the caſe in queſtion, where the Succeſſor is not known; for if he had been, we ſhould have heard of him
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:49847:79"/>before now. And, what is the reaſon that it ſhould then in the former caſe devolve to Lords and Commons, but that there is no King? And they being the Repreſentative Body of the Kingdom, are the only remaining apparent parts of the Government, and are only to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the Defect by providing a Succeſſor. And, is here not the ſame Reaſon here? We are without a King, I am ſure I do not know of any that we have: If that fall out to be the caſe now, that will inſer a Vacancy with a witneſs; and it will be of neceſſity that the Lords and Commons take care to ſupply it.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> G—E—e.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lords,</p>
                  <p>We are led, and, I think, out of the Way, into a very large Field, hunting after the Conſequences of a Vote not yet ſetl'd or agreed unto: We have, as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, nothing but the Vote it ſelf to conſider of, or debate upon: We do not intend to prejudice any Legal Right: But what the conſequences of this Vote may be, before the Vote it ſelf be paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:49847:80"/>I believe no Man can reaſonably pretend to aſcertain, unleſs he have the Spirit of Prophecy.</p>
                  <p>The Throne may be Vacant as to the Poſſeſſion, without the excluſion of one that has a Right to the Succeſſion, or a Diſſolution of the Government in the Conſtitution; neither will there be room for the Objection of a King <hi>de facto,</hi> and not <hi>de jure,</hi> which ſome of the Lords were pleaſed to expreſs their Fears of.</p>
                  <p>This Gentleman that ſtands by me in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanced in a Record, and that was miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, as a Preſident for the proceeding in this Caſe; it was only mention'd by him to ſhew, that by uſing the word <hi>Vacant</hi> the Commons did no more than our Anceſtors did before us; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was not an unknown word or thing to have the Throne Vacant.</p>
                  <p>We do apprehend we have made a right and apt Concluſion from the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, for otherwiſe all the Vote is but Hiſtorical.</p>
                  <pb n="175" facs="tcp:49847:80"/>
                  <p>We declare the Late King hath broke the Original Contract, hath violated the Fundamental Laws, and hath with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn himſelf out of the Kingdom, that he hath <hi>Abdicated,</hi> actually Renounced, the Government.</p>
                  <p>What occaſion was there for ſuch a Declaration as this, if nothing were concluded from it? That were only to give the Kingdom a compendious Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of thoſe Miſeries they have too well learnt by feeling them.</p>
                  <p>Therefore there was a neceſſity to make ſome Concluſion; and none ſo natural as this; That we are left with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a King in the words of the Vote; that the Throne is thereby <hi>Vacant,</hi> which it may be as to the Poſſeſſion, and yet the Right of Succeſſion no way preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diced.</p>
                  <p>But, my Lords, we come here, by the Commands of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, to debate the Reaſons of their Vote and your Lordſhips Amendments,
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:49847:81"/>not to diſpute what will be the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences, which is not at preſent our Province.</p>
               </sp>
               <p>And ſo the Conference ended, and the Members of each Houſe returned to their reſpective Houſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Die Jovis</hi> 7<hi rend="sup">mo</hi> Feb. 1688.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>A Meſſage from the Lords, by Sir <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Atkins</hi> and Sir <hi>Edward Nevill.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Mr. <hi>Speaker,</hi>
                  </salute>
               </opener>
               <p>The Lords have commanded us to tell you, That they have agreed to the Vote ſent them up of the 28th of <hi>January</hi> laſt, (touching which there was a free Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference yeſterday) without any Altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:49847:81"/>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
